<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English mans doctor. Or the schoole of Salerne Or [ph]ysicall obserua[ti]ons for the perfect preseruing of the bodie of man in continuall health. [Wh]ereunto [is] adioyned precepts for the pr[e]seruation of health. Written by [Hen]ricus Ronsouius for [the p]riuate vse of his sons. And now published for all those that desire to [preser]ue their bodies in [perfect] health.</title>
            <title>Regimen sanitatus Salernitatum. English</title>
            <author>Johannes, de Mediolano.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848667</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848667</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13777</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13777)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1692:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English mans doctor. Or the schoole of Salerne Or [ph]ysicall obserua[ti]ons for the perfect preseruing of the bodie of man in continuall health. [Wh]ereunto [is] adioyned precepts for the pr[e]seruation of health. Written by [Hen]ricus Ronsouius for [the p]riuate vse of his sons. And now published for all those that desire to [preser]ue their bodies in [perfect] health.</title>
                  <title>Regimen sanitatus Salernitatum. English</title>
                  <author>Johannes, de Mediolano.</author>
                  <author>Harington, John, Sir, 1560-1612.</author>
                  <author>Hobbes, Stephen, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>S. H.</author>
                  <author>Rantzau, Henrik, 1526-1598. De conservanda valetudine liber. English.</author>
                  <author>Ronsovius, Henricus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44]; [4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Printed] by William Stansby, for the Widdow Helme, [and] are to be sold at her shoppe in Sa[in]t Dunstanes Church-yard in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[L]ondon :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Joannes de Mediolano.</note>
                  <note>Translated in verse by Sir John Harington.</note>
                  <note>"De valetudine conseruanda, or the preservation of health, .. Collected out of Henricus Ronsouius .. and now published .. By S.H." has separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous. It is a prose translation, possibly by Stephen Hobbes, of "De conservanda valetudine liber" by Henrik Rantzau.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page and other leaves torn, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13777:1"/>
            <p>THE ENGLISH MANS DOCTOR. OR <hi>The Schoole of Salerne. OR</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>YSICALL OBSERVA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ON FOR THE PER<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſreuing of the bodie of Man in continuall Health.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ereunto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> adioyned Precepts for the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſeruation of Health.</p>
            <p>Written by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>NRICVS RONSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIVS for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> priuate vſe of his Sons.</p>
            <p>And now p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed for all thoſe that deſire to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their bodies in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> health.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>by <hi>William Stansby,</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Widdow <hi>Helme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are to be ſold at her Shoope in Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Dunſtans Church-yard in Fleet-ſtreete.</hi> 1617.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:2"/>
                  <head>THE PRINTER TO the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, the care that I haue of thy health, appeares in beſtowing theſe Phyſicall rules vpon thee: neither needeſt thou bee aſhamed to take leſſons out of this Schoole: for our beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>octors ſcorne not to reade the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It is a little</hi> Academie, <hi>where euery man may be a Graduate, and proceed Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in the ordering of his owne bodie. It is a Garden, where all things grow that are neceſſarie for thy health. This medicinall Tree grew firſt in</hi> Salerne; <hi>from thence it was remoued, and hath borne fruit and bloſſomes along time in</hi> England. <hi>It is now replanted in a wholeſome ground, and new earth caſt about it by the hand of a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Gardiner, to keepe it ſtill in flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13777:3"/>
                     <hi>Much good husbandry is beſtowed vpon it: yet whatſoeuer the coſt bee, thou reapeſt the ſweetneſſe of it for a ſmall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. It came to me by chance, as a Jewell that is found, whereof notwithstandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> am not couetous, but part the Treaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt my Country-men. The Auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> the paines, is to me vnknowne, and I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> this Childe of his into the open world wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out his conſent. Bring it vp therefore we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> I beſeech thee, and hope (as I doe) that he will not bee angry, finding this a Traueller abroad, when by this trauell ſo many of his own Countrey are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifoldly bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farewell.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomia">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:3"/>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <head>Ad Librum.</head>
                     <l>GO Booke, and (like a Merchant) new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tell in how ſtrange a traffick thou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Vpon the Countrey which the Sea-god ſaues</l>
                     <l>And loues ſo deare; he bindes it round with w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Caſt Anchor thou, and impoſt pay to him</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Swans vpon the breſt of ISIS ſwim.</l>
                     <l>But to the people that doe loue to buy,</l>
                     <l>(It skills not for how much) each nouelty</l>
                     <l>Proclaime an open Mart, and ſell good cheape,</l>
                     <l>What thou by trauell and much coſt doſt reape,</l>
                     <l>Bid the gay Courtier, and coy Lady come,</l>
                     <l>The Lawyer, Townſman, and the countrie groome</l>
                     <l>'Tis ware for all: yet thus much let them know,</l>
                     <l>There are no drugs heere fetcht from <hi>Mex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>o,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor gold from <hi>India,</hi> nor that ſtinking ſmoake,</l>
                     <l>Which Engliſh gallants buy, themſelues to choake,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſilkes of <hi>Turkie,</hi> nor of <hi>Barbary,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thoſe luſcious <hi>Canes,</hi> where our rich Sug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs lie.</l>
                     <l>Nor thoſe hot drinkes that make our wits to dance</l>
                     <l>The wilde <hi>Canaries:</hi> nor thoſe Grapes of <hi>France,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13777:4"/>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ich make vs clip our Engliſh, nor thoſe wares</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> fertile <hi>Belgia,</hi> whoſe wombe compares</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>th all the world for fruite, tho now with ſcarres</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r body be all ore defac'd by warres:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, tell them what thou bringſt exceeds the wealth</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f al theſe Countries for thou bringſt them health</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <pb facs="tcp:13777:4"/>
                     <head>In Librum.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>WIt, Learning, Order, Elegance of Phraſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Health, and the Art to lengthen out our daie</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Philoſophie, Phyſicke, and Poeſie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And that skill which death loues not,</hi> (Surgery)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Walkes to refreſh vs, Ayres moſt ſweete and cleare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A thriftie Table, and the wholeſom'ſt cheare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All ſorts of graine, all ſorts of fleſh, of fiſh,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Fowle, and (laſt of all) of fruits a ſeuer all diſh:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Good Breakefaſts, Dinners, Suppers, after-meales,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The hearbe for Sallads, and the hearbe that heales,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phyſicions Counſell, Pothecaries pils,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Without the ſumming vp of coſtly bils,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wines that the braine ſhall ne're intoxicate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Strong Ale and Beere at a more eaſier rate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then Water from the Fountaine: clothes (nor deere)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For the foure ſeuerall quarters of the yeere,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Meates both for Proteſtant and Puritan,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With meanes ſufficient to maintaine a man.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If all theſe things thou want'st, no farther looke,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All this, and more then this, lyes in this Booke.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <pb facs="tcp:13777:5"/>
                     <head>In Laudem Operis.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>THe Gods vpon a time in counſell ſitting,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To rule the world what creature was moſt fitting,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At length from God to God this ſentence ran,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o forme a creature like themſelves (called Man)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ng made, the world was giuen him built ſo rarely,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> workman can come neere it: hung ſo fairely,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat the Gods viewing it, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uer-ioyed:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> grieu'd that it ſhould one day be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtroyed:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ardens had Man to walke in, ſet with trees</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat ſtill were bearing: But (neglecting theſe)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> long'd for fruits vnlawfull, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ell to riots,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> bodie by ill dyets.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pent (what was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> him) like a prodigall heyre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And had of earth, of hell, or heauen no care,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or which the earth was curſt, and brought forth w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ds,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oyſon euen lurking in our faireſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ds,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> heauen was hid, and did in darkeneſſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ne:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hilſt hell kept fires continuall, that ſhould burne</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> very ſoule, if ſtill it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And giue it torments that ſhould neuer die,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>; How bleſt is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> the Deities,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Built up the</hi> Schoole of Health, <hi>to make him wiſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:5"/>
                  <head>THE SALERNE Schoole.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe <hi>Salerne Schoole</hi> doth by theſe lines impa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>All health to <hi>Englands King,</hi> and doth aduiſe</l>
                     <l>From care his head to keepe, from wrath his heart,</l>
                     <l>Drinke not much wine, ſup light, and ſoone ariſe,</l>
                     <l>When meat is gone, long ſitting breedeth ſmart</l>
                     <l>And after-noone ſtill waking keepe your eyes.</l>
                     <l>When mou'd you find your ſelfe to <hi>Natures Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Forbeare them not, for that much danger breeds,</l>
                     <l>Vſe three Phyſicions ſtill; firſt Doctor <hi>Quiet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Next Doctor <hi>Merry-man,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Dyet.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Riſe carely in the morne, and ſtraight remember,</l>
                     <l>With water cold to waſh your hands and eyes,</l>
                     <l>In gentle faſhion retching enery member,</l>
                     <l>And to refreſh your braine when as you riſe,</l>
                     <l>In heat, in cold, in <hi>Iuly</hi> and <hi>December.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Both comb your head, and rub your teeth likewiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>If bled you haue, keep coole, if bath'd keepe warm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>If din'd, to ſtand or walke will do no harme.</l>
                     <l>Three things preſerue the ſight, <hi>Graſſe, Glaſſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At Ene'n ſprings, at morning viſit mountains.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:6"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>R.</hi> be in the month, their iudgements erre,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>at thinke that ſleepe in after-noone is good:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>R.</hi> be not therein, ſome men there are</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>at thinke a little nap breeds no ill bloud:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t if you ſhall herein exceed too farre,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> hurts your health, it cannot be with ſtood:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ong ſleepe at after-noones by ſtirring ſumes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reeds <hi>Slouth, and Agues, Aking heads and Rheumes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he morſture bred in Brest, in Iawes and Noſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Are eal'd Catars, or Tyſique, or the Poſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great harmes haue growne, &amp; maladies exceeding,</l>
                     <l>By keeping in a little blaſt of wind:</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Cramps,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dropſies, Collickes</hi> haue their breeding,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Mazed Brames</hi> for want of vent behind:</l>
                     <l>Beſides we finde in ſtories worth the reading,</l>
                     <l>A certaine <hi>Remane Emperour</hi> was ſo kind,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Claudius</hi> by name, he made a Proclamation,</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Scape</hi> to be no loſſe of reputation.</l>
                     <l>Great ſuppers do the ſtomacke much offend,</l>
                     <l>Sup light if quiet you to ſleepe intend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:6"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To keepe good dyet, you ſhould neuer feed</l>
                     <l>Vntill you finde your ſtomacke cleane and void</l>
                     <l>Of former eaten meate, for they do breed</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Repletion,</hi> and will cauſe you ſoone be cloid,</l>
                     <l>None other rule but appetite ſhould need,</l>
                     <l>When from your mouth a moyſture cleare dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> void</l>
                     <l>All <hi>Peares and Apples, Peaches, Milke and Cheeſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Salt meates, red Deere, Hare, Beefe and Goat:</hi> all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are meates, that breed ill bloud, and Melancholy,</l>
                     <l>If ſicke you be, to feede on them were folly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Egges newly laid, are nutritiue to eate,</l>
                     <l>And roſted Reare are eaſie to digeſt,</l>
                     <l>* Freſh <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> wine is good to drinke with mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Broth</hi> ſtrengthens nature aboue all the reſt,</l>
                     <l>But broth prepar'd with floure of fineſt wheat,</l>
                     <l>Well boild, and full of ſat fat for ſuch are beſt.</l>
                     <l>* The <hi>Prieſts</hi> rule is (a <hi>Prieſts</hi> rule ſhould be true)</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Egges are beſt, are long, and white and new</l>
                     <l>Remember eating new laid Egges and ſoft,</l>
                     <l>For euery Egge you eate you drinke as oft.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:7"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ine <hi>Manchet</hi> feeds too fat, <hi>Milke</hi> fils the veines,</l>
                     <l>New Cheeſe doth nouriſh, ſo doth fleſh of Swine;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Dowcets of ſome beaſts, the marrow, braines,</l>
                     <l>And all ſweet taſting fleſh, and pleaſant wine,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oft Egges (a cleanely diſh in houſe of Swaines)</l>
                     <l>Ripe Figs and Rayſins, late come from the Vine:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>huſe wine you meane ſhall ſerue you all the ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Well-ſauo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d, taſting well, and coloured cleere.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iue qualities there are, wines praiſe aduancing,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Strong, Beautifull, and Fragrant, coole and dancing.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>White <hi>Muskadel,</hi> and <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> wine,</hi> and <hi>Greeke,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Do make mens wits and bodies groſſe and fat;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Red wine</hi> doth make the voyce oft-time to ſeeke,</l>
                     <l>And hath a binding qualitie to that;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>anarie,</hi> and <hi>Madera,</hi> both are like</l>
                     <l>To make one leane indeed: (but wot you what)</l>
                     <l>Who ſay they make one leane, would make one laffe</l>
                     <l>They meane, They make one leane vpon a ſtaffe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wine, women, Baths,</hi> by Art or Nature warme,</l>
                     <l>Vs'd or abus'd do men much good or harme.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:7"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sixe things, that here in order ſhall enſue,</l>
                     <l>Againſt all poyſons haue a ſecret power,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Peare, Garlicke, Reddiſh roots, Nuts, Rape, and Rue,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But <hi>Garlicke</hi> chiefe; for they that it deuoure,</l>
                     <l>May drinke, &amp; care not who their drinke do brew:</l>
                     <l>May walke in aires infected euery houre.</l>
                     <l>Sith <hi>Garlicke</hi> then hath power to ſaue from death,</l>
                     <l>Beare with it though it make vnſauory breath,</l>
                     <l>And ſcorne not <hi>Garlicke,</hi> like to ſome that thinke,</l>
                     <l>If onely makes men winke, and drinke, and ſtinke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though all ill ſauours do not breed infection,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſure infection commeth moſt by ſmelling,</l>
                     <l>Who ſmelleth ſtill perfumed, his complexion</l>
                     <l>Is not perfum'd by Poet <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>tials</hi> telling,</l>
                     <l>Yet for your lodging roomes giue this direction,</l>
                     <l>In houſes where you mind to make your dwelling,</l>
                     <l>That neere the ſame there be no euill ſents</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f puddle-waters, or of excrements,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t aire be cleere and light, and free from faults,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>at come of ſecret paſſages and vaults.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:8"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> wine haue ouer night a ſurfet brought,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> thing we wiſh to you ſhould happen ſeeld:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen early in the morning drinke a draught,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd that a kind of remedie ſhall yeeld,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut gainſt all ſurfets, vertues ſchoole hath taught</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o make the gift of temperance a ſhield:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he better wines do breed the better humors,</l>
                     <l>The worſe, are cauſes of vnwholeſome tumors,</l>
                     <l>In meaſure drinke, let wine be ripe, not thicke,</l>
                     <l>But cleere and well alaid, and freſh and quicke,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The like aduice we giue you for your Beere,</l>
                     <l>We will it be not ſowre, and yet be ſtale:</l>
                     <l>Well boild, of harty graine, and old and cleare,</l>
                     <l>Nor drinke too much nor let it be too ſtale:</l>
                     <l>And as there be foure ſeaſons in the yeere,</l>
                     <l>In each a ſeuerall order keepe you ſhall.</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Spring</hi> your dinner muſt not much exceed,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Summers</hi> heate but little meate ſhall need:</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Autumne</hi> ware you eate not too much fruite:</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Winters</hi> cold full meates do fitteſt ſuite.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:8"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If in your drinke you mingle <hi>Rew</hi> with <hi>Sage,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>All poyſon is expeld by power of thoſe,</l>
                     <l>And if you would withall Luſts heat aſſwage,</l>
                     <l>Adde to them two the gentle flowre of Roſe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Would not be ſea-ſicke when ſeas do rage,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sage-water</hi> drinke with wine before he goes.</l>
                     <l>* <hi>Salt, Garlicke, Parſly, Pepper, Sage, and Wine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Make ſawces for all meates both courſe and fine,</l>
                     <l>Of waſhing of your hands much good doth riſe,</l>
                     <l>Tis wholeſome, cleanely, and relieues your eyes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Eate not your bread too ſtale, nor eate it hot,</l>
                     <l>A little Leuend, hollow-bak't and light:</l>
                     <l>Not freſh, of pureſt graine that can be got,</l>
                     <l>The cruſt breeds choller both of browne &amp; white,</l>
                     <l>Yet let it be well bak't or eate it not,</l>
                     <l>How er'e your taſte therein may take delight.</l>
                     <l>* <hi>Porke</hi> without wine is not ſo good to eate,</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Sheepe</hi> with wine, it medicine is and meate,</l>
                     <l>Tho Intrailes of a beaſt be not the beſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et are ſome intrailes better then the reſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:9"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>me loue to drinke new wine not fully fin'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> for your health we wiſh that you drinke none,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſuch to dangerous ſluxes are inclin'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſides, the Lees of wine doe breed the ſtone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>me to drinke onely water are aſſign'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t ſuch by our conſent ſhall drinke alone.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r water and ſmall beere we make no queſtion,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e enemies to health and good digeſtion:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d <hi>Horace</hi> in a verſe of his rehearſes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>at <hi>Water-drinkers</hi> neuer made good verſes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he choyſe of meate to health doth much auaile,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>rſt Veale is wholeſom meat, &amp; breeds good bloud</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Capon, Hen, and Chicken, Partridge, Quaile,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e Pheſant, Woodcock, Larke, &amp; Thruſh be good,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Heath-cocke wholeſome is, the doue, the raile,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd all that doe not much delight in mud.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aire ſwans ſuch loue your beauties make me beare you,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat in the diſh I eaſily could forbeare you.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ood ſport it is to ſee a <hi>Mallard</hi> kil'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut with their fleſh, your fleſh ſhould not be fil'd,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:9"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As choyce you make of Fowle, ſo make of Fiſh,</l>
                     <l>If ſo that kinde be ſoft, the great be beſt,</l>
                     <l>If firme, then ſmall, and many in a diſh:</l>
                     <l>I need not name, all kinds are in requeſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pike, Trowt,</hi> and <hi>Pearch,</hi> from water freſh I wiſh,</l>
                     <l>From Sea, <hi>Bace, Mullet, Brean,</hi> and <hi>Souls</hi> are beſt</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Pyke</hi> a rauening tyrant is in water,</l>
                     <l>Yet he on land yeelds good fiſh ne're the later,</l>
                     <l>If <hi>Eeles</hi> and <hi>Cheeſe</hi> you eate, they make you hoarſe</l>
                     <l>But drinke apace thereto, and then no force.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some loue at meals to drink ſmal draughts and oft,</l>
                     <l>But fancie may herein and cuſtome guide,</l>
                     <l>If Egges you eate, they muſt be new and ſoft.</l>
                     <l>In Peaſe good qualities and bad are tryed,</l>
                     <l>To take them with the skinne that growes aloft,</l>
                     <l>They windie be, but good without their hide.</l>
                     <l>In great conſumptions learn'd Phyſicions thinke,</l>
                     <l>'Tis good a <hi>Goat</hi> or <hi>Camels</hi> milke to drinke,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cowes-milke</hi> and <hi>Sheepes</hi> doe well, but yet an <hi>Aſſes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is beſt of all, and all the other paſſes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Milke</hi> is for <hi>Agues</hi> and for <hi>Head-ach</hi> naught,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t if from <hi>Agues</hi> fit you feele you free,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>eete-butter</hi> wholeſome is, as ſome haue taught,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> cleanſe and purge ſome paines that inward be.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Whay,</hi> though it be contemn'd, yet it is thought</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o ſcoure and cleanſe, and purge in due degree:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> For healthie men may <hi>Cheeſe</hi> be wholeſome food,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut for the weake and ſickly 'tis not good,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>heeſe</hi> is an heauie meate, both groſſe and cold,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd breedeth Coſtineſſe both new and old.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cheeſe</hi> makes complaint that men on wrong ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</l>
                     <l>Do ſlander it, and ſay it doth ſuch harme,</l>
                     <l>That they conceale his many good conditions,</l>
                     <l>How oft it helpes a ſtomack cold to warme,</l>
                     <l>How faſting 'tis preſcrib'd by ſome Phyſicions,</l>
                     <l>To thoſe to whom the flux doth giue alarme:</l>
                     <l>We ſee the better ſort thereof doth eate,</l>
                     <l>To make as 'twere a period of their meate;</l>
                     <l>The poorer ſort, when other meate is ſcant,</l>
                     <l>For hunger eate it to releeue their want.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:10"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Although you may drinke often while you dine,</l>
                     <l>Yet after dinner touch not once the cup,</l>
                     <l>I know that ſome Phyſicions doe aſſigne</l>
                     <l>To take ſome liquor ſtraight before they ſup:</l>
                     <l>But whether this be meant by broth or wine,</l>
                     <l>A controuerſie 'tis not yet tane vp:</l>
                     <l>To cloſe your ſtomack well, this order ſutes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cheeſe</hi> after fleſh, <hi>Nuts</hi> after fiſh or fruits.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſome haue ſaid, (belecue them as you will)</l>
                     <l>One <hi>Nut</hi> doth good, two hurt, the third doth kill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some <hi>Nut</hi> 'gainſt poyſon is preſeruatiue:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Peares</hi> wanting wine, are poyſon from the tree,</l>
                     <l>But bak't Peares counted are reſtoratiue,</l>
                     <l>Raw Peares a poyſon, bak't a medicine be,</l>
                     <l>Bak't Peares a weake dead ſtomack doe reuiue,</l>
                     <l>Raw Peares are heauie to digeſt we ſee,</l>
                     <l>Drinke after Peares, take after Apples order</l>
                     <l>To haue a place to purge your ſelfe of ordure.</l>
                     <l>Ripe <hi>Cherries</hi> breed good bloud, and help the ſtone,</l>
                     <l>If <hi>Cherry</hi> you doe eate and <hi>Cherry-ſtone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:11"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ole <hi>Damſens</hi> are, and good for health, by reaſon</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ey make your intrailes ſoluble and ſlacke,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t <hi>Peaches</hi> ſteepe in wine of neweſt ſeaſon,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uts</hi> hurt the teeth, that with their teeth they crack,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ith euery <hi>Nut</hi> 'tis good to eate a <hi>Raiſon.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r though they hurt the ſpleen, they help the back,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> plaiſter made of Figges, by ſome mens telling,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s good againſt all kernels, boyles and ſwelling,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Poppy</hi> ioyn'd, it drawes out bones are broken,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Figges</hi> are lice ingendred, Luſt prouoken.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Eate <hi>Medlers,</hi> if you haue a looſeneſſe gotten,</l>
                     <l>They bind, and yet your vrine they augment,</l>
                     <l>They haue one name more fit to be forgotten,</l>
                     <l>While hard and ſound they be, they be not ſpent,</l>
                     <l>Good <hi>Medlers</hi> are not ripe, till ſeeming rotten,</l>
                     <l>For medling much with <hi>Medlers</hi> ſome are ſhent.</l>
                     <l>New <hi>Reniſh-wine</hi> ſtirres vrine, doth not binde:</l>
                     <l>But rather looſe the Belly breeding winde,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ale</hi> humors breeds, it addes both fleſh and force;</l>
                     <l>Tis looſing, coole, and vrin doth enforce.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:11"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sharpe vineger doth coole, withall it dries,</l>
                     <l>And giues to ſome ill humor good correction:</l>
                     <l>It makes one melancholy, hurts their eyes,</l>
                     <l>Not making fat, nor mending their complexion</l>
                     <l>It leſſons ſperme, makes appetite to riſe,</l>
                     <l>Both taſte and ſcent is good againſt infection,</l>
                     <l>* The <hi>Turnep</hi> hurts the ſtomack, winde it breed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Stirres vrine, hurts his teeth thereon that feedet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who much thereof will feed, may wiſh our Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Would well allow of <hi>Claudius</hi> proclamation.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It followes now what part of euery beaſt</l>
                     <l>Is good to eate: firſt know the Heart is ill,</l>
                     <l>It is both hard and heauy to digeſt.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Tripe</hi> with no good iuyce our fleſh doth fill:</l>
                     <l>The Lites are light, yet but in ſmall requeſt:</l>
                     <l>But outer parts are beſt in Phyſicks skill.</l>
                     <l>* If any braines be good, (which is a queſtion)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hens</hi> braine is beſt and lighteſt of digeſtion.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> In <hi>Fennel-ſeed,</hi> this vertue you ſhall finde,</l>
                     <l>Foorth of your lower parts to driue the winde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:12"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ennell,</hi> vertues foure they doe recite,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> it hath power ſome poyſons to expell,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, burning Agues it will put to flight,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſtomack it doth cleanſe and comfort well:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> fourthly, it doth keepe and cleanſe the ſight,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> thus the ſeed and hearbe doth both excell.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> for the two laſt told, if any ſeed</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>h <hi>Fennell</hi> may compare, 'tis <hi>Annis-ſeed:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e <hi>Annis-ſeed</hi> be ſweete, and ſome more bitter,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> pleaſure theſe, for medicine thoſe are fitter.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>me Natures reaſon, far ſurmounts our reading,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e feele effects the cauſes oft vnknowne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ho knows the cauſe why <hi>Spodium</hi> ſtancheth blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>podium</hi> but aſhes of an Oxes bone)</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> learne herein to praiſe his power exceeding,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat vertue gaue to wood, to hearbs, to ſtone;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Liuer, <hi>Spodium; Mace,</hi> the heart delights,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he braine likes <hi>Muske,</hi> and <hi>Lycoras</hi> the Lites;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Spleene is thought much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted with <hi>Capers,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n ſtomack, <hi>Gallingale,</hi> alwaies ill vapors.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:12"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sauce would be ſet with meate vpon the table,</l>
                     <l>Salt is good ſauce, and had with great facilitie:</l>
                     <l>Salt makes vnſauourie vyands manducable,</l>
                     <l>To driue ſome poyſons out, Salt hath abilitie,</l>
                     <l>Yet things too ſalt are ne're commendable:</l>
                     <l>They hurt the ſight, in nature cauſe debilitie,</l>
                     <l>The ſcab and itch on them are euer breeding,</l>
                     <l>The which on meates too ſalt are often feeding:</l>
                     <l>Salt ſhould be firſt remou'd, and firſt ſet downe</l>
                     <l>At table of the Knight, and of the Clowne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As taſtes are diuers, ſo Phyſicions hold</l>
                     <l>They haue as ſundry qualities and powre,</l>
                     <l>Some burning are, ſome temperate, ſome cold,</l>
                     <l>Cold are theſe three, the <hi>Tart,</hi> the <hi>Sharpe,</hi> the <hi>ſowr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Salt, bitter, byting, burne as hath beene told,</l>
                     <l>Sweet, fat and freſh, are temperate euery houre.</l>
                     <l>* Foure ſpeciall vertues hath a ſop in wine,</l>
                     <l>It maketh the teeth white, it cleares the eyne,</l>
                     <l>It addes vnto an emptie ſtomack fulneſſe,</l>
                     <l>And from a ſtomack fill'd, it takes the dulneſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:13"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to an vſe you haue your ſelfe betaken,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> any dyet, make no ſudden change,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cuſtome is not eaſily forſaken,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>a though it better were, yet ſeemes it ſtrange,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ng vſe is as a ſecond nature taken,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ith nature cuſtome walkes in equall range,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Good dyet is a perfect way of curing:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d worthy much regard and health aſſuring.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> King that cannot rule him in his dyet,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ill hardly rule his Realme in peace and quiet.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>y that in Phyſick will preſcribe you food,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>x things muſt note we heere in order touch,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>rſt <hi>what it is,</hi> and then <hi>for what 'tis good,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd <hi>when</hi> and <hi>where, how often,</hi> and <hi>how much.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ho note not this, it cannot be with-ſtood,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey hurt, not heale, yet are too many ſuch.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>rts</hi> broth doth looſe, the ſubſtance bind,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hus play they faſt and looſe, and all behind:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut yet if at one time you take them both,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he ſubſtance ſhall giue place vnto the broth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:13"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In Phyſicke <hi>Mallowes</hi> haue much reputation,</l>
                     <l>The very name of <hi>Mallow</hi> ſeemes to ſound,</l>
                     <l>The roote thereof will giue a kind purgation,</l>
                     <l>By them both men and women good haue found,</l>
                     <l>To womens monthly flowers they giue laxation,</l>
                     <l>They make men ſoluble that haue beene bound.</l>
                     <l>And leſt wee ſeeme in <hi>Mallowes</hi> prayſes partiall,</l>
                     <l>Long ſince hath <hi>Horace</hi> praiſed them and <hi>Martiall</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>* The worms that gnaw the wombe &amp; neuer ſtint,</l>
                     <l>Are kil'd, and purg'd, and driuen away with <hi>Mint.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But who can write thy worth (O ſoueraigne <hi>Sage!</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Some aske how man can die, where thou doſt grow,</l>
                     <l>Oh that there were a medicine curing age,</l>
                     <l>Death comes at laſt, tho death comes ne're ſo ſlow:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sage</hi> ſtrengths the ſinewes, ſeuers heat doth ſwage,</l>
                     <l>The Palſy helpes, and rids of mickle woe.</l>
                     <l>In Lattin <hi>(Salu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>)</hi> takes the name of ſafety,</l>
                     <l>In Engliſh <hi>(Sage)</hi> is rather wiſe then crafty.</l>
                     <l>Sith then the name betokens wiſe and ſauing,</l>
                     <l>We count it natures friend and worth the hauing.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:14"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ke <hi>Sage</hi> and <hi>Primroſe, Lauender</hi> and <hi>Creſſes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ith <hi>Walwort</hi> that doth grow twixt lime and ſtone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r he that of theſe hearbes the iuyce expreſſes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d mix with powder of a <hi>Caſtor-ſtone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ay breed their eaſe whom palſy much oppreſſes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r if this breed not helpe, then looke for none.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Rew</hi> is a noble hearbe to giue it right,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o chew it faſting, it will purge the ſight.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne quality thereof yet blame I muſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t makes men chaſte, and women fils with luſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Faire Ladies, if theſe Phyſicke rules be true,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Rew</hi> hath ſuch ſtrange qualities as theſe.</l>
                     <l>Eate little <hi>Rew,</hi> leſt your good husband, (REW)</l>
                     <l>And breed betweene you both a ſhrew'd diſeaſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rew</hi> whets the wit, and more to pleaſure you,</l>
                     <l>In water boyld, it rids the roome of fleas.</l>
                     <l>I would not to you Ladies, <hi>Onyons</hi> praiſe,</l>
                     <l>Saue that they make one faire (<hi>Aeſclapius</hi> ſaies)</l>
                     <l>Yet taking them requires ſome good direction,</l>
                     <l>They are not good alike for each complexion.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:14"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If vnto <hi>Choller</hi> men be much inclin'd,</l>
                     <l>'Tis thought that <hi>Onyons</hi> are not good for thoſe,</l>
                     <l>But if a man be flegmatique (by kind)</l>
                     <l>It does his ſtomacke good, as ſome ſuppoſe:</l>
                     <l>For Oyntment iuyce of <hi>Onyons</hi> is aſſign'd,</l>
                     <l>To heads whoſe haire fals faſter then it growes:</l>
                     <l>If <hi>Onyons</hi> cannot helpe in ſuch miſhap,</l>
                     <l>A man muſt get him a <hi>Gregorian</hi> cap.</l>
                     <l>And if your hound by hap ſhould bite his maſter,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Hony, Rew,</hi> and <hi>Onyons</hi> make a plaſter.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The ſeed of <hi>Muſtard</hi> is the ſmalleſt graine,</l>
                     <l>And yet the force thereof is very great,</l>
                     <l>It hath a preſent power to purge the braine,</l>
                     <l>It adds vnto the ſtomacke force and heat:</l>
                     <l>All poiſon it expels, and it is plaine,</l>
                     <l>With ſuger 'tis a paſſing ſauce for meate.</l>
                     <l>She that hath hap a husband bad to bury,</l>
                     <l>And is therefore in heart not ſad, but merry,</l>
                     <l>Yet if in ſhew good manners ſhee will keepe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Onyons</hi> and <hi>Muſtard-ſeed</hi> will make her weepe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:15"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hough <hi>Violets</hi> ſmell ſweete, <hi>Nettles</hi> offenſiue,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et each in ſeuerall kind much good procures,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he firſt doth purge the heauy head and penſiue,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ecouers ſurfets, falling ſickeneſſe cures:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ho <hi>Nettles</hi> ſtinke, yet make they recompence,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f your belly by the Collicke paine endures,</l>
                     <l>Againſt the Collicke Nettle-ſeed and hony</l>
                     <l>Is Phyſick: better none is had for money.</l>
                     <l>It breedeth ſleepe ſtaies vomits, fleams doth ſoften,</l>
                     <l>It helpes him of the Gowte that eates it often.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Cleane <hi>Hyſop</hi> is an hearbe to purge and clenſe</l>
                     <l>Raw flegmes, and hurtfull humors from the breſt,</l>
                     <l>The ſame vnto the lungs great comfort lends,</l>
                     <l>With hony boyl'd: but farre aboue the reſt,</l>
                     <l>It giues good colour, and complexion mends,</l>
                     <l>And is therefore with women in requeſt:</l>
                     <l>With Hony mixt, <hi>Cinquefoyle</hi> cures the Canker,</l>
                     <l>That eates out inward parts with cruell ranker,</l>
                     <l>But mixt with wine, it helpes a grieued ſide,</l>
                     <l>And ſtaies the vomit, and the laske beſide.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:15"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ellecompane</hi> ſtrengthens each inward part,</l>
                     <l>A little looſeneſſe is thereby prouoken,</l>
                     <l>It ſwageth griefe of minde, it cheeres the heart,</l>
                     <l>Allaieth wrath, and makes a man faire ſpoken:</l>
                     <l>And drunke with Rew in wine, it doth impart</l>
                     <l>Great help to thoſe that haue their bellies broken,</l>
                     <l>Let them that vnto choller much incline,</l>
                     <l>Drinke <hi>Penny-royall</hi> ſteeped in their wine.</l>
                     <l>And ſome affirme that they haue found by tryall,</l>
                     <l>The paine of Gowt is cur'd by <hi>Penny-royall.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To tell all <hi>Creſſes</hi> vertues long it were,</l>
                     <l>But diuers patients vnto that are debter:</l>
                     <l>It helpes the teeth, it giues to bald men haire,</l>
                     <l>With Hony mixt, it Ring worms kils and Tetter:</l>
                     <l>But let not women that would children beare</l>
                     <l>Feed much thereof, for they to faſt were better.</l>
                     <l>An hearbe there is takes of the Swallowes name,</l>
                     <l>And by the Swallowes gets no little fame,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Pliny</hi> writes (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ho ſome thereof make doubt)</l>
                     <l>It helpes yong Swallowes eyes when they are out.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>reene Willow</hi> though in ſcorne it oft is vſ'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et ſome are there in it not ſcornefull parts,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t killeth wormes, the iuice in eares infuſ'd,</l>
                     <l>With Vineger: the barke deſtroyeth warts:</l>
                     <l>But at one quality I much haue muſ'd,</l>
                     <l>That addes and bates much of his good deſerts.</l>
                     <l>For writers old and new, both ours and forren,</l>
                     <l>Affirme the ſeed make women chaſt and barren.</l>
                     <l>Take <hi>Saffron</hi> if your heat make glad you will,</l>
                     <l>But not too much for that the heart may kill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Greene Leekes</hi> are good, as ſome Phyſicians ſay,</l>
                     <l>Yet would I chooſe how er'e I them beleeue,</l>
                     <l>To weare <hi>Leekes</hi> rather on Saint <hi>Dauids</hi> day,</l>
                     <l>Then eate the <hi>Leeke</hi> vpon Saint <hi>Dauids</hi> Eue,</l>
                     <l>The bleeding at the noſe <hi>Leekes</hi> iuice will ſtay,</l>
                     <l>And women bearing children much releeue.</l>
                     <l>* <hi>Blacke Pepper</hi> beaten groſſe you good ſhall finde,</l>
                     <l>If cold your ſtomacke be, or full of winde:</l>
                     <l>White <hi>Pepper</hi> helps the cough, and fleame it riddeth</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Agues</hi> fit to come it oft forbiddeth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:16"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our hearing is a choyce and dainty ſenſe,</l>
                     <l>And hard to men, yet ſoone it may be mard,</l>
                     <l>Theſe are the things that breed it moſt offence,</l>
                     <l>To ſleepe on ſtomacke full and drinking hard,</l>
                     <l>Blowes, fals, and noyſe, and faſting violence,</l>
                     <l>Great heate and ſodaine cooling afterward;</l>
                     <l>All theſe, as is by ſundry proofes appearing,</l>
                     <l>Breed tingling in our eares, and hurt our hearing:</l>
                     <l>Then thinke it good aduice, not idle talke,</l>
                     <l>That after Supper bids vs ſtand or walke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You heard before what is for hearing naught,</l>
                     <l>Now ſhall you ſee what hurtfull is for ſight:</l>
                     <l>Wine, women, Bathes, by art to nature wrought,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leekes, Onions, Garlicke, Muſtard-ſeed, fire</hi> and <hi>light,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Smoake, bruiſes, duſt, Pepper</hi> to powder brought,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beanes, Lentiles, ſtrains, Wind, Tears,</hi> &amp; <hi>Phoebus</hi> bright,</l>
                     <l>And all ſharpe things our eye-ſight do moleſt:</l>
                     <l>Yet watching hurts them more then all the reſt;</l>
                     <l>* Of <hi>Fennell, Veruin, Kellidon, Roſes, Rew:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is water made, that will the ſight renew.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:17"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in your teeth you hap to be tormented,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> meane ſome little wormes therein do breed:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hich paine (if heed be tane) may be preuented,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y keeping cleane your teeth when as you feed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urne Frankincenſe (a gum not euill ſented)</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t Henbane vnto this, and Onyon ſeed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd in a Tunnell to the Tooth that's hollow,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onuey the ſmoake thereof, and eaſe ſhall follow.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> By Nuts, Oyle, Eeles, and cold in head,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y Apples and raw fruits is hoarſeneſſe bred.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To ſhew you how to ſhun raw running Rheumes,</l>
                     <l>Exceed not much in meate, in drinke, and ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>For all exceſſe is cauſe of hurtfull fumes,</l>
                     <l>Eate warme broth warme, ſtriue in your breath to keep,</l>
                     <l>Vſe exerciſe that vapours ill conſumes:</l>
                     <l>In Northern winds abroad do neuer peepe.</l>
                     <l>If <hi>Fiſtula</hi> do riſe in any part,</l>
                     <l>And ſo procure your danger and your ſmart,</l>
                     <l>Take <hi>Arſenicke, Brimſtone,</hi> mixt with <hi>Lime</hi> and <hi>Sope,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And make a tent, and then of cure there's hope.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:17"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If ſo your head doe paine you oft with aking,</l>
                     <l>Faire water or ſmall beere drinke then or neuer,</l>
                     <l>So may you ſcape the burning fits and ſhaking</l>
                     <l>That wonted are to company the Feuer.</l>
                     <l>* If with much heate your head be ill in aking,</l>
                     <l>To rub your head and temples full perſeuer,</l>
                     <l>And make a bath of Morrell (boyled warme)</l>
                     <l>And it ſhall keepe your head from further harme,</l>
                     <l>* A Flix dangerous euill is, and common,</l>
                     <l>In it ſhun cold, much drinke, and ſtraine of women.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To faſt in Summer doth the body dry,</l>
                     <l>Yet doth it good, if thereto you enure it,</l>
                     <l>Againſt a ſurfet vomiting to try,</l>
                     <l>Is remedy, but ſome cannot endure it.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſome ſo much themſelues found helpe thereby,</l>
                     <l>They go to ſea a purpoſe to procure it.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Foure ſeaſons of the yeare there are in all,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Summer</hi> and the <hi>Winter, Spring</hi> and <hi>Fall:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In euery one of theſe, the rule of reaſon</l>
                     <l>Bids keepe good diet, ſuiting euery ſeaſon.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:18"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e ſpring is moiſt, of temper good and warme,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen beſt it is to bathe, to ſweate, and purge,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen may one ope a veine in either arme,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> boyling bloud or feare of agues vrge:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> recreation doth no harme,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et may too much thereof turne to a ſcourge.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n Summers heat (when choller hath dominion)</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oole meates and moiſt are beſt in ſome opinion:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he <hi>Fall</hi> is like the <hi>Spring,</hi> but endeth colder,</l>
                     <l>With Wines and Spice the Winter may be bolder.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now if perhaps ſome haue deſire to know,</l>
                     <l>The number of our bones, our teeth, our veines,</l>
                     <l>This verſe enſuing plainly doth it ſhew,</l>
                     <l>To him that doth obſerue, it taketh paines:</l>
                     <l>The teeth thriſe ten, and two, twiſe eight arow.</l>
                     <l>Eleu'n ſcore bones ſaue one in vs remaines:</l>
                     <l>For veines, that all may vaine in vs appeare,</l>
                     <l>A veine we haue for each day in the yeare:</l>
                     <l>All theſe are like in number and connexion.</l>
                     <l>The difference growes in bigneſſe and complexion.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:18"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Foure humors raigne within our bodies wholly,</l>
                     <l>And theſe compared to foure Elements,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sanguine, Choller, Flegme,</hi> and <hi>Melancholy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The latter two are heauie, dull of ſence,</l>
                     <l>Th'other two are more Iouiall, quicke and Iolly,</l>
                     <l>And may be likened thus without offence,</l>
                     <l>Like ayre both warme and moiſt, is <hi>Sanguine</hi> clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Like fire doth <hi>Choler</hi> hot and drie appeare.</l>
                     <l>Like water cold and moiſt is <hi>Flegmatique,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Melancholy</hi> cold, drie earth is like.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Complexions</hi> cannot vertue breed or vice,</l>
                     <l>Yet may they vnto both giue inclination,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sanguine</hi> game-ſome is, and nothing nice,</l>
                     <l>Loue Wine, and Women, and all recreation,</l>
                     <l>Likes pleaſant tales, and news, playes, cards &amp; dice</l>
                     <l>Fit for all company, and euery faſhion:</l>
                     <l>Though bold, not apt to take offence, not irefull,</l>
                     <l>But bountifull and kinde, and looking cheerefull:</l>
                     <l>Inclining to be fat, and prone to laughter,</l>
                     <l>Loues mirth, &amp; Muſick, cares not what comes after</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:19"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>rpe <hi>Choller</hi> is an humour moſt pernitious,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> violent, and fierce, and full of fire,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> quicke conceit, and therewithall ambitious,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ir thoughts to greater fortunes ſtill aſpire,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ud, bountifull ynough, yet oft malicious,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ight bold ſpeaker, and as bold a lyar,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> little cauſe to anger great enclin'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ch eating ſtill, yet euer looking pin'd:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> yonger yeares they vſe to grow apace,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Elder hairie on their breſt and face.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he <hi>Flegmatique</hi> are moſt of no great growth,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>clining to be rather fat and ſquare:</l>
                     <l>Giuen much vnto their eaſe, to reſt and ſloth,</l>
                     <l>Content in knowledge to take little ſhare,</l>
                     <l>To put themſelues to any paine moſt loth.</l>
                     <l>So dead their ſpirits, ſo dull their ſences are:</l>
                     <l>Still either ſitting, like to folke that dreame,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe ſtill ſpitting, to auoid the flegme:</l>
                     <l>One qualitie doth yet theſe harmes repaire,</l>
                     <l>That for the moſt part <hi>Flegmatique</hi> are faire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:19"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Melancholly</hi> from the reſt doe varie,</l>
                     <l>Both ſport and eaſe, and company refuſing,</l>
                     <l>Exceeding ſtudious, euer ſolitary,</l>
                     <l>Inclining penſiue ſtill to be, and muſing,</l>
                     <l>A ſecret hate to others apt to carry:</l>
                     <l>Moſt conſtant in his choiſe, tho long a chuſing,</l>
                     <l>Extreme in loue ſometime, yet ſeldome luſtfull,</l>
                     <l>Suſpitious in his nature, and miſtruſtfull,</l>
                     <l>A wary wit, a hand much giuen to ſparing,</l>
                     <l>A heauy looke, a ſpirit little daring.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now though we giue theſe humors ſeuerall names</l>
                     <l>Yet all men are of all participant,</l>
                     <l>But all haue not in quantitie the ſame,</l>
                     <l>For ſome <hi>(in ſome)</hi> are more predominant,</l>
                     <l>The colour ſhewes from whence it lightly came,</l>
                     <l>Or whether they haue bloud too much or want.</l>
                     <l>The watrie Flegmatique are faire and white,</l>
                     <l>The Sanguine Roſes ioyn'd to Lillies bright,</l>
                     <l>The Chollerick more red; the Melancholly,</l>
                     <l>Alluding to their name, are ſwart and colly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:20"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f <hi>Sanguine</hi> humor doe too much abound,</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſignes will be thereof appearing cheefe,</l>
                     <l>The face wil ſwell, the cheekes grow red and round</l>
                     <l>With ſtaring eyes, the pulſe beate ſoft and breefe,</l>
                     <l>The veines exceed, the belly will be bound,</l>
                     <l>The temples and the fore-head full of griefe,</l>
                     <l>Vnquiet ſleepes, that ſo ſtrange dreames will make</l>
                     <l>To cauſe one bluſh to tell when he doth wake:</l>
                     <l>Beſides the moiſture of the mouth and ſpittle,</l>
                     <l>Will taſte too ſweet, and ſeeme the throat to tickle</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If <hi>Choler</hi> doe exceed, as may ſometimes,</l>
                     <l>Your eares will ring, and make you to be wakefull,</l>
                     <l>Your tongue will ſeeme all rough, and oftentimes</l>
                     <l>Cauſe vomits, vnaccuſtomed and hatefull.</l>
                     <l>Great thirſt, your excrements are full of ſlime,</l>
                     <l>The ſtomack ſqueamiſh, ſuſtenance vngratefull:</l>
                     <l>Your appetite will ſeeme in nought delighting,</l>
                     <l>Your heart ſtill grieued with continuall byting,</l>
                     <l>The pulſe beate hard and ſwift, all hot extreme,</l>
                     <l>Your ſpittle ſowre, of fire-worke oft you dreame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:20"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If <hi>Flegme</hi> aboundance haue due limits paſt,</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſignes are heere ſet downe will plainely ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>The mouth will ſeeme to you quite out of taſt,</l>
                     <l>And apt with moyſture ſtill to ouer-flow:</l>
                     <l>Your ſides will ſeeme all ſore downe to the waſt,</l>
                     <l>Your meate wax loathſome, your digeſtion ſlow:</l>
                     <l>Your head and ſtomacke both in ſo ill taking,</l>
                     <l>One ſeeming euer griping t'other aking:</l>
                     <l>With empty veines the pulſe beate ſlow and ſoft,</l>
                     <l>In ſleepe, of Seas and riuers dreaming oft.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if that dangerous humor ouer-raigne,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Melancholy,</hi> ſometime making mad,</l>
                     <l>Theſe tokens then will be appearing plaine,</l>
                     <l>The pulſe beate hard, the colour darke and bad:</l>
                     <l>The water thin, a weake fantaſticke braine,</l>
                     <l>Falſe grounded ioy, or elſe perpetuall ſad;</l>
                     <l>Affrighted oftentimes with dreames like viſions,</l>
                     <l>Preſenting to the thoughts ill apparitions,</l>
                     <l>Of bitter belches from the ſtomacke comming,</l>
                     <l>His eare (the left eſpeciall) euer burning.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>inſt theſe ſeuerall humors ouerflowing,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſeuerall kinds of Phyſicke may be good,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> diet, drinke, hot baths, whence ſweat is growing</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>th purging, vomiting, and letting bloud:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ich taken, in due time, not ouerflowing,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ch malladies infection is withſtood.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e laſt of theſe is beſt, if skill and reaſon,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſpect age, ſtrength, quantity, and ſeaſon,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f ſeuenty from ſeuenteene, if bloud abound,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he opening of a veine is healthfull found.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of Bleeding many profits grow and great,</l>
                     <l>The ſpirits and ſenſes are renewed thereby:</l>
                     <l>Tho theſe men ſlowly by the ſtrength of meat,</l>
                     <l>But theſe with wine reſtor'd are by and by.</l>
                     <l>By bleeding, to the marrow commeth heat,</l>
                     <l>It maketh cleane your braine, relieues your eye,</l>
                     <l>It mends your appetite, reſtoreth ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>Correcting humours that do waking keepe:</l>
                     <l>All inward parts and ſenſes alſo clearing,</l>
                     <l>It mends the voyce, touch, ſmell &amp; taſt, &amp; hearing.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Three ſpeciall Months <hi>(September, April, May)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>There are, in which 'tis good to ope a veine;</l>
                     <l>In theſe 3 Months the Moone beares greateſt ſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then old or yong that ſtore of bloud containe,</l>
                     <l>May bleed now, though ſome older wizards ſay</l>
                     <l>Some dayes are ill in theſe, I hold it vaine:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>September, April, May,</hi> haue dayes a peece,</l>
                     <l>That bleeding do forbid, and eating Geeſe,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe are they forſooth of May the firſt,</l>
                     <l>Of other two, the laſt of each are worſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But yet thoſe daies I grant, and all the reſt,</l>
                     <l>Haue in ſome caſes iuſt impediment:</l>
                     <l>As firſt, if nature be with cold oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>Or if the Region, Ile, or Continent</l>
                     <l>Do ſcorch or freize, if ſtomacke meat deteſt:</l>
                     <l>If Baths or Venus late you did frequent,</l>
                     <l>Nor old, nor yong, nor drinkers great are fit,</l>
                     <l>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in long ſickeneſſe, nor in raging fit,</l>
                     <l>Or in this caſe if you will venture bleeding,</l>
                     <l>The quantity muſt then be moſt exceeding.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:22"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen you to bleed intend, you muſt prepare</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>me needfull things both after and before,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arme water and ſweet oyle, both needfull are,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d wine, the fainting ſpirit to reſtore:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e binding clothes of linnen, and beware,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>at all the morning you do ſleepe no more:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>me gentle motion helpeth after bleeding,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d on light meates a ſpare and temperate feeding:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o bleed doth cheere the penſiue, and remoue</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he raging ſuries bred by burning loue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ake your inciſion large and not too deepe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat bloud haue ſpeedy iſſue with the fume,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o that from ſinewes you all hurt do keepe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or may you (as I toucht before) preſume</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſixe enſuing houres at all to ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſt ſome ſlight bruiſe in ſleepe cauſe an apoſtume:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ate not of milke, nor ought of milk compounded,</l>
                     <l>Nor let your brain with much drink be confounded</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ate no cold meats, for ſuch the ſtrength impaires,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd ſhun all miſty and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>holeſome aires.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:22"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Beſides the former rules for ſuch as pleaſes,</l>
                     <l>Of letting bloud to take more obſeruation,</l>
                     <l>Know in beginning of all ſharpe diſeaſes,</l>
                     <l>'Tis counted beſt to make euacuation:</l>
                     <l>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> old, to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> yong, both letting bloud diſpleaſes.</l>
                     <l>By yeares and ſickneſſe make your computation.</l>
                     <l>Firſt in the Spring for quantity, you ſhall,</l>
                     <l>Of bloud take twiſe as much as in the Fall:</l>
                     <l>In Spring and Summer let the right arme blood,</l>
                     <l>The Fall and Winter for the left are good.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Liuer,</hi> Spring &amp; Summers bleeding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Fall and Winter, hand and foot doth mend,</l>
                     <l>One veine cut in the hand, doth help exceeding,</l>
                     <l>Vnto the ſpleene, voyce, breſt, and intrailes lend,</l>
                     <l>And ſwages griefes that in the heart are breeding.</l>
                     <l>But here the <hi>Salerne Schoole</hi> doth make an end:</l>
                     <l>And here I ceaſe to write, but will not ceaſe</l>
                     <l>To wiſh you hue in health, and die in peace:</l>
                     <l>And ye our Phyſicke rules that friendly read,</l>
                     <l>God grant that Phyſicke you may neuer need.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:23"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>De valetudine conſeruanda,</hi> OR <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>HE PRESER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATION OF HEALTH, <hi>OR</hi> A DYET FOR THE HEALTHFVLL MAN. Collected out of HENRICVS RONSOVIVS, which he wrought for the vſe of his Sonnes: And now publiſhed for the helpe of all thoſe, that deſire their owne HEALTHS.</p>
                  <p>By S. H.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Stansby, for</hi> the Widow <hi>Helmes.</hi> 1617.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:24"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:24"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull SIR EDWARD PIT, Knight, of Keere Court, one of his MAIESTIES Iuſtices of Peace, in the Countie of Worceſter, &amp;c. And to the right Worſhipfull SIR IAMES PIT, his Sonne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt all the parts of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick (Right Worſhipfull) I ſuppoſe there is none to be preferd before that part, which preſerueth health, and preuenteth ſickneſſe, for as</hi> Tully <hi>ſaith, Health is the most perfect ſtate of mans body in this life, and the only end and intention, whereunto the Phyſician diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all his doings, which ſtate to continue and to enioy, is much better then to haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the recouery of a ſickneſſe, that by ill dyet is taken, as it is better to ſtand fast, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen to fall, and riſe againe; and better to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>epe ſtill a Fortreſſe or a Caſtle, then when</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13777:25"/>
                     <hi>we haue ſuffered the Enemy to enter, to reſcue it againe, for as the Poet ſaith:</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Aegrius eijcitur quam non admittitur hoſpes.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And becauſe as</hi> Cornelius Celſus <hi>ſaith, that all medicines do in a manner hurt the ſtomack, and be of euill nutriment. And therefore</hi> Aeſclipiades <hi>did endeuour most to cure his Patients by dyet; which dyet, Right Worſhipfull, I haue here deſcribed and publiſhed to the view of the world, and haue ſheltered it vnder the title of your Name, praying you to accept the ſame with a willing minde, conſidering that I haue no better thing to preſent you with: And as that Perſian Monarch did dayne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue from a poore man a handfull of cold water, ſo your Worſhip will accept this poore labor, which I now preſent you with, which ſhall encourage me hereafter to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with ſome other labours of more worth. In the meane while, I humbly take my leaue, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting both you and all yours vnto the protection of the Almightie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips moſt obſeruant S. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:25"/>
                  <head>THE PRESERVATION OF HEALTH, <hi>OR</hi> A DYET FOR THE HEALTHFVL MAN.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The cauſes of corruption and destruction of our humane bodies.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT we may come to our purpoſe, the firſt and chiefeſt cauſe of corruption and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Bodies, of old Age, Death, and all other miſeries, which doe happen vnto vs in this life, is the fall of our firſt Parents, and the reliques of Sinne, remayning in our corrupt Nature, as the Apoſtle doth witneſſe in the eighth Chapter of the Romans: <hi>Corpus noſtrum,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13777:26"/>
morti deſtinatum eſt propter pcccatum.</hi> For, euen as death is the laſt of all euills, which may afflict vs in this life; euen ſo, by the name of Death we endure in this life all miſeries and afflictions; Heere-hence come our errours which leade vs by our blinde will, and through the perſwaſion of the Deuill driue vs to commit all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and euill, wherby we accumulate and heape vp the iuſt wrath and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, to afflict vs with euery kinde of diſeaſe, miſerie, and calamitie.</p>
                     <p>Another cauſe of diſeaſes, deſtruction, and deprauation of our bodies, is the ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and maleuolent influence of the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Planets, and the infelicitie of our temperaments: for, as in euery thing there are certayne naturall properties, which God from euerlaſting hath endued with naturall effects; ſo euery effect and vertue is incited in our bodies from Heauen, which God created not only in a certayne order and greatneſſe, that we ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Yeeres, Dayes, and Moneths, but that there ſhould be ſignes alſo from whence wee might take certayne Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of things to come.</p>
                     <p>For the inferior bodies doe depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13777:26"/>
the Superior, and are contayned in a certayne mutuall knowledge amongſt themſelues; for the Superior doth infuſe a certayne ſecret force and vertue into the Inferior bodies, by which the humours of our bodies are changed, increaſed, and diminiſhed according to the placing and qualitie of the Starres: and this is more cleerely and euidently taught vs by daily experience the Miſtris of all things, then that it needeth farther demonſtration. If no man will giue credit to our wordes, let him conſider the Moone which doth challenge vnto her ſelfe the chiefe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Humours, and they ſhall well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their error. Seeing then it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that the humours of our bodies are gouerned by the Superior bodies: And of the euill humours of our bodies to grow Diſeaſes, and from diſeaſe death; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not vnworthily of death: and the cauſe of other diſeaſes to depend in ſome part vpon the celeſtiall bodies, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
                     <p>Beſides this there are two other kindes of cauſes, that doe change and deſtroy our bodies, which doe grow from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Planets.</p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13777:27"/>
                     <p>One kinde is that, that is ingendred with vs, and is therefore ſaid to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, neceſſarie, and ineuitable, and they are in number three, that is, Dryneſſe, which by the courſe of Age bringeth to death, a daily waſting of ſubſtance, or the great varietie and mobilitie of the matter in our bodies, and the abundance of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements.</p>
                     <p>Another kinde of them are, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen outward, and therefore are called Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, of which the reaſon is ſaid to be twofold, for ſome of them are which doth not change or affect our bodies of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; for although when theſe things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, their hurt may be by vs auoyded, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, there are ſome of them that our life may be ſafe without them. They are ſuch things which doe bruiſe, hurt, and wound our bodies, which for the moſt part hapneth by ſome outward force, as in the warres, and other caſes of Fortune, as either being drowned or made away with poyſon.</p>
                     <p>There are other things alſo, which are ſaid of neceſſitie to alter Mans body, which although we may auoide particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, yet generally we cannot, when we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13777:27"/>
cannot liue without them. Theſe things, I ſay, doe deſtroy and ouerthrow the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature, conſtitution, and naturall health of man, if they be not rightly vſed as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and the ſtate of the body requireth. And thoſe are thoſe ſixe things, which are called not naturall, which we will conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in particular; which ſixe things are placed in our power and election, and they are of ſixe kindes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1.</note>The firſt is, Ayre, Water, and Fire.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">2.</note>The ſecond is, Meate and Drinke, and all thoſe things which are giuen the body for nouriſhment.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">3.</note>The third is, Motion and Reſt, both of the whole body, as of euery part thereof.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">4.</note>The fourth is, Sleepe and Watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">5.</note>The fifth is, Excretion or Expulſion of excrements or retention, vnder which is contayned the opening of a veine, Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Vomit, auoyding of Urin, Sweate, Bathing, the act of Generation, and ſuch like.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">6</note>The ſixth are, the Symptoms, Pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations, Affections or Accidents of the minde, ſuch as are Feare, Anger, Sorrow,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13777:28"/>
Ioy, and ſuch like, of which we will ſpeak more afterwards.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things being duely and rightly vſed, doe conſerue man in good health, but vſed contrarily, they deſtroy; for, as health doth conſiſt in a meane and a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocritie, ſo alſo in a meane vſe of things neceſſary it is conſerued.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Generall precepts to conſerue the Health.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Haue declared vnto you the chiefe cauſes, through which the diuers mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, deſtructions, and corruptions of our bodies doe ariſe. Now, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie I will declare vnto you alſo thoſe things, which if we vſe them in right or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and manner, doe contayne the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of life, reſtore health loſt, and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſome kindes of diſeaſes and expell them.</p>
                     <p>For this thing it is firſt needfull and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, that you know certainely and be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13777:28"/>
ſure of, that although the celeſtiall bodies doe exerciſe a certayne force and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vertue, in the affaires of Man, yet notwithſtanding, GOD Almightie, the Worke-man and Creator of all Nature and Humane things, being the Lord of Life and Death, who hath the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Inferior bodies that cannot be remoued, but that he doth gouerne and rule the influence of all Stars and Planets, and remoue the courſe and efficacy of them; and likewiſe doth moderate all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations that grow from the Planets, and oftentimes according to his great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth turn away diſeaſes, and change them into better: ſometimes alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his ſecret and iuſt iudgement for our ſinnes, to exaſperate and turne them into worſe.</p>
                     <p>For the diuine Maieſtie is not in the Starres, which the God-head hath framed for the profit and conſeruation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, neither is it incloſed within a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne fatall neceſſitie, as it were ſhut vp in priſon, but doth worke freely, and as the chiefe cauſe doth gouerne and moderate all other cauſes. This therefore eternall God, the moſt louing Father of our Lord
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13777:29"/>
Ieſus Chriſt, which proroged the life of King <hi>Hazechias</hi> for fifteene yeeres, is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to be prayed vnto daily, that he would beſtow vpon vs alſo a long and a ſafe life, with a right conſtitution as well of body as ſtrength of minde, and to preſerue the ſame: for rightly is it ſaid:
<q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aſtra valent aliquid, plus pia vota valent,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aſtra regunt mundum, ſed regit aſtra Deus.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cedunt aſtra Deo, precibus Deus ipſe piorum.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
Next, when for our ſinnes our bodies are affected with often and diuers kindes of diſeaſes, we muſt carefully ſtriue that we gouerne the inclinations and wandering motions of our mindes, and that we vſe a bridle to our outward members, and that we doe not only flye wickedneſſe, but that we auoide the occaſions alſo thereof. It becommeth you, my deare Sonnes, to vſe this diligence in the gouernement of your life and manners, and chiefly to embrace true Religion, and due obedience and loue to your Parents, which if you ſhall doe, God will in like manner, as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> giue vnto you hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and long life: for as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith truely in the 1. of <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Pietas ad omnia vtilis eſt, &amp;c.</hi> Godlineſſe is profitable vnto
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13777:29"/>
all things, which hath the promiſe of the life preſent, and of that that is to come: the which in ſome manner was vnderſtood by an Ethnick, <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> King of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrians, where he ſaith, <hi>Qui mentem arden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ad opus pietatis intenderit, labile corpus ſeruabit:</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pietatem eſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem, &amp; fundamentum omnium virtutum:</hi> That Godlineſſe is the mother and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all vertues. Secondly, when it is ſaid, that the Starres be the working cauſes of deſtruction and mutation, and the cauſes of diuers diſeaſes in our bodies: and whereas the obſeruation of the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall effects is not forbidden, I will that you take this care, that as well the yeerly directions, as the figures of your natiuity be obſerued, which I haue diligently and exactly computated, I leaue to euery one of you: which notwithſtanding you ſhall examine without all ſuperſtition, and ſhall be aduiſed by the iudgement of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Aſtrologians and Phyſicians, that you may the better auoid the euill foreſeene, and the good things ſhall be brought to their wiſhed euent, for that is true which ſome doe affirme, that <hi>coelum eſſe fatalem picturam in coel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſti tabula;</hi> and very well
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13777:30"/>
was it ſaid by <hi>Hipp.</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> the Princes of Phyſicians, that the Arte of phyſicke, without the ſupportation of the Heauens, to be oftentimes in vaine, yea alſo often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be hurtfull.</p>
                     <p>This obſeruation doth profit very much for the preſeruation of the health, and for the preuention of diſeaſes; therefore you muſt regard the more your naturall incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, with the greater vigilancy, that you may bee the better able to gouerne your manners, and the euents of which we are admoniſhed by Aſtrologers, &amp; which wee fore-know, wee may the more eaſier beare. Auoid and decline them more wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that you may ſeeme to paſſe them ouer prouidently and diſcreetly, without griefe or tediouſneſſe: for, free-will and electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is left to vs, ſo farforth that by the help of God, a minde ſupported, may be able to reſiſt the allurements of the Fleſh and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Deuill, to rule and gouerne the affections<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if ſome great calamitie againſt an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> man may be preſaged and declared by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Starres, we may be able to flye and auoid it; notwithſtanding in which matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> would that you ſhould regard the counſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> of honeſtie: for if we may flye and auoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13777:30"/>
the perill that hangeth ouer our heads, without ſhame, we ſhall not refuſe it, for better is it with honeſtie to die quickly, then with ſhame to liue long: therefore, we muſt thinke that Reaſon, and the beſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect, to be gouerned by the Heauens, neither is the libertie of the minde, and our actions, reſtrayned to the neceſſitie of the Starres.</p>
                     <p>Hitherto in generall, we haue briefly declared, by what meanes we may defend vs from euills, and diſeaſes of euery kind: and to defend vs from the other deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our bodies, which diligence, if the children of God ſhall diligently inuocate him, they ſhall happily auoid them.</p>
                     <p>Now, that we may follow our purpoſe, I will entreat of thoſe things, which in ſome manner reſteth in our induſtrie, of which if we vſe them rightly and lawfully we ſhall nouriſh health, and conſerue it, but otherwiſe we ſhall ouerthrow and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13777:31"/>
                     <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Speciall precepts of preſeruing Health.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THat we may begin from the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Health is a conſtitution of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in which wee are neither tormented with griefes, nor hindred in the actions of our life, for if the body ſhall decline from that conſtitution, it is ſickneſſe: to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue health, according to <hi>Raſis in Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore,</hi> is in motion and reſt, meate &amp; drinke, neither to obſerue a iuſt meaſure in ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities and expulſions, the houſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places wherein we liue, to be made ſweet with odors, according as reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, and agreeing with the time, and to meet with euill accidents before they take their increaſe, and to refraine volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe and delightfull pleaſures, and to conſerue cuſtome. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, That health is preſerued with the knowledge of a mans owne body, as well in thoſe things which are wont to profit as hurt, for in thoſe things in which conſiſteth conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, from them corruption ſpringeth, for as conſeruation is made by the like thing, ſo curation is made by its contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a little otherwiſe ſaith <hi>Iſidore,</hi> where he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13777:31"/>
ſaith, <hi>Eam eſſe integritatem corporis, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantiam naturae ex calido &amp; humido, in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cum illa conſiſtit. Sequitur, qui plurimum calidi &amp; humidi habent, hos maximè eſſe lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaeuos: qui verò contrariae ſunt naturae, frigidi &amp; ſirci, hos citius ſeneſcere &amp; mori.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For as healthfull men are gouerned by the foure Humours, ſo the infirme are hurt, and when humours encreaſe more then of equitie they ſhould, they bring forth ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſo thoſe that are by nature onely groſſe, do ſooner die then thinner bodies, for they haue little bloud and ſpirits. But as the conſeruation of health doth conſiſt in the order of euery thing, being lawfully vſed, the iuſt qualitie, quantitie, and time being obſerued, we haue ſpoken of: Now of the ayre that doth incompaſſe our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, we will ſpeake of.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of the ayre.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="section">
                        <p>THe ayre by it ſelfe is hot and moyſt, and the attraction thereof is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary vnto all liuing creatures, that if the wayes of reſpiration bee intercepted, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13777:32"/>
occluded, they preſently die, and all of vs haue experience, that the conſtitution of the bodie is often changed, eyther by the temperature or diſtemperature of the ayre: therefore we muſt prouide with all our ſtudy, to chuſe the beſt ayre, as much as may be.</p>
                        <p>For that is the beſt ayre which to euerie one is natiue, for as the Philoſopher ſaith, <hi>Vniuſcuiuſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> locus naturalis ſui eſt locati con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruantius:</hi> beſides, a temperate ayre, pure, cleare, and thinne, which lyeth open, and is free from ſtinkes, infection, or putrifacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; is to be choſen. And on the contrary, that ayre is moſt bad and hurtfull, which is troubleſome, cloudie, impure, ſtinking, ſhowrie, putride, cloſe, which neither wind nor Sunne doth penetrate, nor purge: in like manner, that is good ayre, which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth neither venenoſity, nor other malign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> qualitie, through the ſtanding waters which in the Summer time are corrupte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> with a peſtilent ayre, or with the vapour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> exhalations, or infected with foeculent ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cretions: ſo that ayre is moſt maliciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> which ſpringeth from dunghills, ſincke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> and other peſtiferous places, which dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> oppreſſe the heart, and make a difficultie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13777:32"/>
breathing, which is ouer hot, or ouer cold, for an hot ayre diſſolueth the ſpirits, it ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerateth thirſt, it diminiſheth the vitall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and hindereth digeſtion. A cold ayre doth ingender the Aſthma and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarrhes: and as this impure ayre doth vitiat the vitall ſpirits, ſo muſt wee be carefull by all meanes to beware of it; ſo then we muſt draw an ayre that is pure and temperate, for except a good ayre be drawne in daily, whereby our naturall heat may be ventila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, tempered and cooled, our health muſt needes bee troubled and endangered, of which it appeareth, where it is ſaid:
<q>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Satius eſſe ſub dio verſari, quam</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Cubiculis vndi<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> clauſis immorari.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </q>
                        </p>
                        <p>It behooueth alſo for vs to obſerue this thing, that in cold ſeaſons it ſhall be fit to vſe an hotte ayre, or fire for hot things in a cold time: moyſt in a drie, and drie in a moiſt aire, is chiefely fitting and agreeing: alſo in daily diſeaſes, we ſee it is ſometimes very profitable to change the ayre, for ſometimes change of ayre and place doth recouer health that is loſt. But whereas the ayre oftentimes is mooued and changed with the windes, and odors, for the winde is no other thing then the aire moued with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13777:33"/>
the ſtirring and prouoking of vapours, of which, and of ſweete ſmells, it ſhall not be amiſſe ſomewhat to ſpeake of.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>Of windes, and ſweete ſmelling ſauours.</head>
                        <p>THe North-wind of al other is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the beſt and wholeſomeſt, and the Eaſt doth challenge to it ſelfe the next place, and what winde ſoeuer doth mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately coole, doth drie and make cleere our habitations: therefore it muſt be towards the North and Eaſt, for the temperature of the ayre and the wind; for too much wind is hurtfull very much to the ſence, both of the lungs, the eyes and eares: but that which attaineth to odoraments, and ſweet ſmells: it is manifeſt, as it were, the ayre to bee nouriſhed by the ſpirits, but moſt quickly by odors the braine and heart is ſtrengthened, and the minde refreſhed; which refreſhment the body alſo doth feele the pleaſure and recreation.</p>
                        <p>A naughtie ſtinking ayre, is corrected and amended by odoraments and ſuffumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; but there is a very great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: for look what ayre we draw in, ſuch and the like ſpirits goe out from vs.</p>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13777:33"/>
                        <p>Odors and ſmells that are oner-hot, are not by me approued, becauſe it filleth the head, and ingendreth the catarrh, for the temperature it ſelfe of the braine, being a meane betweene hot and cold, doth chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reioyce in things that are temperate: and on the other ſide it is much offended and hurt by the contrary: therefore ſometimes thoſe odors are to be mixed and changed, as if cold doth raigne, let the odors decline to heat; and if heat doth beare ſway, then frame that they may be of cold operation.</p>
                        <p>Of Roſes therefore, Violets and Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, Campher, Sanders and Roſe-water, which are cold things: on the other ſide, of Cinamon, Citron rynds, Orenge peeles, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes, Amber, Muske, which are hot; of which you may vſe at your pleaſure. Odors are not only drawne by the noſtrills, but there muſt bee application to the breſt and ſtomacke, Treacle, Mithridate, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, Amber, Angelica, and ſuch like, which are thought to haue vertue againſt venome: no leſſe comfort to recreate your ſpirits, ariſeth out of gardens, where-hence ariſeth ſweete ſmells and ſauours: alſo to vſe ſweete ſmelling hearbes, flowers and ruſhes at the time of the yeere, conuenient
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13777:34"/>
to the conſtitution and ſtate of the bodie, and to caſt about the court, and in the chambers, the leaues of Withies, of Roſes, Violets, Vine-leaues, Origanum, wilde Time, Time, Lauender, Myrtils, Quinces, Peares, the flowers of Orenges, Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, and other ſuch like: and alſo to ſprinkle the chamber with Roſe-water, or the water of the flowres of Orenges, and other like: alſo to euaporate the place with vineger, and ſometimes alſo in your cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to burne perfumes, fragrant and ſweet ſmelling.</p>
                        <p>What ſweete ſmells, fumes or torches I am wont to vſe; I will heere ſet downe, that hauing a care to the temperature and ſtate of the body, you may vſe alſo.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prescription">
                        <head>A deſcription of an odoriferous water.</head>
                        <p>TAke an equall weight of Roſe-water, with the beſt white wine, Roſe-vini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the fourth part, Suger-candie, a third part; diſſolue it in thoſe things; ſome adde a little Saffron: with this water waſh the hands and face, the ioynts and eyes, and therewith cleanſe the teeth, and beſprinkle the reſt of the clothes.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13777:34"/>
                     <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Meates and Drinks.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="section">
                        <p>IN meate and drinke wee muſt conſider theſe ſixe things, firſt, the Subſtance: then the Quantitie: third, the Qualitie: fourth, Cuſtome: fift, the Time: and laſtly, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. We muſt alſo vnderſtand, that it is beſt and moſt wholeſome to vſe meates that be ſimple: for meates that be ſimple are moſt wholeſome and profitable; but many and ſundrie ſorts of meates are very vnhealth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and hurtfull to our bodies: our elders, which liued very long, and without ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, were wont to eate at one meale fleſh only, and at another bread only: yet would I not wiſh you (my ſonnes) to accuſtome your ſelues to one only meate, eſpecially if you be yong; for <hi>Galen</hi> expounding the Aphoriſme of <hi>Hipp.</hi> ſaith, That ſuch things as wee haue of long time beene vſed to, although they bee not of the beſt nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they are not ſo dangerous as other things which are farre better, whereunto we haue not beene accuſtomed: wee muſt therefore now and then alter our diet, and vſe to eate ſuch meates as before wee vſed not; neither muſt we bind our ſelues to any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13777:35"/>
one kinde, leſt we be driuen at any time to change our cuſtome, and ſo wee fall ſicke preſently thereupon. <hi>Cornelius Celſus,</hi> a good Phyſicion, giueth counſell, that ſuch as bee in health, ſhould vſe their ordinarie fore, and plaine vſuall diet: and to forbeare much varietie of meats, is beſt and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt, becauſe the ſtomack ſet a work, too too much laboureth, greatly in the dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of ſundry meates at one time. It is thought good to mixe moiſt with drie things, cold with hot, and hot with cold; and thoſe meats which are in the meane or mediocritie of all exceſſe, to be moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable: of which ſort, is bread made of cleane corne, ſufficiently leauened and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately baked. Alſo the fleſh of Hens and Capons, Pheſants, Partriges, Woodcocks, yong Pigeons, Blackbirds, Thruſhes, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and ſuch like ſmall birds. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Fiſhes bred amongſt rocks and ſtones, or about the ſea ſide, and ſuch as in taſte are neither vnpleaſant and vnſauourie, nor yet clammie and vnctious, of the which we will ſpeake particularly hereafter. Now in meats, nothing ſo well encreaſeth good bloud, as when they are well digeſted, for thereby is ended more eaſily the ſecond
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13777:35"/>
concoction, which is in the veines and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and alſo admitteth the third digeſtion, which is in the particular members &amp; parts which be nouriſhed. Alſo there bee ſome meats, betweene whom there is but ſmall difference of digeſtion, as is betweene a Henne and a ſucking Calfe, a Chicken and a Kid, the fleſh of an old Calfe and a yong Bullock: in ſuch reſpects as theſe, where the difference is ſo ſmall, it skilleth not greatly, if they which be ſomewhat hard to digeſt, be eaten before that which is of lighter digeſtion. And this, I ſuppoſe, was the opinion of <hi>Galen,</hi> for heauie meats, and ſuch as bee ſlow of digeſtion, require a ſtronger and greater power digeſtiue: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meats of eaſie digeſtion are firſt to be taken, before thoſe which doe differ ſo far from them in eaſineſſe of concoction.</p>
                        <p>And alſo you muſt take heede of crude and raw meates, and that the ſame be both throughly boyled or roſted, but in any wiſe beware of ſtuffing of your ſelues too much with meate and drinke, nor to irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate and prouoke your appetite with deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſawces, for meates exceſſiuely eaten, although they be of good nouriſhment, commonly they doe ingender crudities,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13777:36"/>
lasks, and vomits. Againe, to take leſſe then neceſſitie and nature doth require, is the cauſe why the body is not nouriſhed, but weakned and made vnable to doe his buſineſſe: for euen as <hi>repletum</hi> hindreth nouriſhment and hurteth nature, ſo all ſorts of too much abſtinence cauſeth vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, hurteth the ſtomack, reſolueth the powers of the body, and increaſeth ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. And euen as an ill dyet bringeth heauineſſe to the body, and dulneſſe to the ſenſes, ſo a good dyet refreſheth the ſpirits and reuiueth the minde, making it more able and actiue to know and practiſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues operations.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>Of Drinke.</head>
                        <p>COncerning drinke at meales, it would not be taken before ſomething hath beene eaten, &amp; at the beginning the drink would be ſtrongeſt, and ſo towards the end more ſmall, if it be Ale or Beere. And if it be Wine, more and more allayed with Water, and the beſt Phyſicians hold, the drinke would rather be mixt with the meate by ſundrie ſmall draughts, then with one great draught at the end of the meale, for the mixture tempereth well the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13777:36"/>
meate without hindrance. A great draught drowneth the meate, and hurteth naturall heate, that then worketh in concoction, and with the weight driueth downe the meate ouer-haſtily. Hot wines and ſweet or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fectioned with ſpices, or very ſtrong Ale or Beere is not good at meales, for thereby the meate is rather corrupted then digeſted, and they make hot and ſtinking vapours to aſcend vp to the braynes; thus I ſuppoſe, I haue ſpoken enough of meate and drinke: I will now end with the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Cornelius Celſus,</hi> which ſaith, that a healthfull man ſhall not binde himſelfe to the rules of phyſick or dyet, but a man whoſe ſtomack is feeble, there ought to be a greater regard that the meate be ſuch, as that either in qualitie or quantitie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be not rebuked or to much oppreſſed.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Exerciſe and Labour.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEcauſe a great part of health doth conſiſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fit and conuenient exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the body, as <hi>Auicen, Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> doe witneſſe, it is therefore
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13777:37"/>
needfull to haue a diligent and carefull conſideration thereunto: labour then or exerciſe is a vehement mouing, the end whereof is the alteration of the breath or winde of man: of exerciſe doe proceed many commodities: And eſpecially three, the firſt is hardneſſe and ſtrength of the members, whereby labour ſhall the leſſe grieue, and the body be more ſtrengthned to endure labour. And that exerciſe or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour doth ſtrengthen the body, as <hi>Galen</hi> witneſſeth in his booke <hi>de Sanitate tuenda.</hi> It is proued by experience in labourers, who for the moſt part be ſtronger then men that liue at eaſe, and can endure grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter toyle, as may be obſerued in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Milo Crotoniatos,</hi> who by the vſe of carrying a Calfe euery day certayne furlongs, was able to carry the ſame being a Bull. The ſecond commoditie of labour is, the increaſe of heate, whereby hapneth the more alteration of things to be dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; alſo more quick alteration and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nouriſhment. The third is more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the breath or winde, whereby the pores are cleanſed, and the excrements of the body naturally expelled. Theſe things are ſo neceſſary to the preſeruation of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13777:37"/>
health, that without them no man may long be without ſickneſſe: for as the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water doth not lightly corrupt, but that which ſtandeth ſtill, euen ſo, bodies exerciſed are for the moſt part more helth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſuch as be idle more ſubiect to ſickneſſe, according to the ſaying of the Poer <hi>Ouid,</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cernis vt ignauum corrumpant otia corpus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Vt capiunt vitium ni moucantur aquae.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
The which thing alſo <hi>Cornelius Celſus</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, where he ſaith, Slothfulneſſe dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the body, it is ſtrengthned by labour, the one doth make vs ſoone old, the other doth make vs long yong.</p>
                     <p>Notwithſtanding in exerciſe ought foure things to be conſidered, that is to ſay, the Time, the things preceding the Qualitie, and the quantitie of exerciſe. As concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the time conuenient to exerciſe in, there ought foure things to be diligently conſidered, firſt, the time, the things prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the quality, and the quantity of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. Firſt, as concerning the time, that the ſtomacke and bowels be ouer-burdened, and the meate not digeſted, or the humors crude or rawe, leſt thereby perill might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low by their conueyance into all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13777:38"/>
                        <hi>Galen</hi> doth ſay, that the time moſt fit for exerciſe, is when both the firſt and ſecond digeſtion is fulfilled, as well in the ſtomacke as in the veines, and that a deſire of eating doth draw neere: for if the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe be ſooner or later, the bodie ſhall ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be filled with raw and crude humors, or elſe yellow choller ſhall be encreaſed. The knowledge of this time is well known by the colour of the Vrine, for that which is like vnto cleare water, ſheweth that the Iuyce which commeth from the ſtomacke, is crude &amp; raw in the veines: that which is wel coloured, neither too high or too low, ſheweth that the ſecond digeſtion is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed perfectly: where the colour is very high or red, it declareth the concoction is too much. Wherefore, when the Vrine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in a temperate colour, neither too red nor too pale, but as it were, gilt, then ſhould we begin our exerciſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Sleepe and Watch.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe commodities of moderate ſleepe, doe appeare by this, that naturall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13777:38"/>
heate which is buſied about the matter, whereof proceedeth nouriſhment, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in the places of digeſtion, and ſo the digeſtion is made better and more perfect by ſleepe, the body is fatter, and the minde more quiet, the humors more temperate. But by much watch all things happen the cleane contrary. The moderation of ſleepe muſt be meaſured by health and ſickneſſe, by age, time, emptineſſe, or fulneſſe of the bodie, and by naturall complexions: as firſt to a man in health, hauing no weakneſſe of nature, and a perfect digeſture of the meat he eateth, a little ſleepe is ſufficient, but to them which haue weak ſtomakes, the ſleep may be the longer. In like manner, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is required both in youth and age at all ſeaſons, winter and Summer. The body being full of ill humors, very little ſleepe is ſufficient, except the humors be crude and raw, for then ſleepe is neceſſary, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth them better then labour.</p>
                     <p>In like manner, where the bodie is long empty, by long ſicknes or abſtinence, ſleep comforteth nature as well in the principal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, as in al the other. As for the length of ſleep, al Authors do agree, that to ſtrong bodies, ſeuen houres in the night is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13777:39"/>
and to thoſe that are weaker, eight houres is enough at the moſt. <hi>Plato</hi> in <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeo,</hi> ſaith, When the world ſhutteth vp her eye, we ſhould alſo cloſe vp our eyes: the eye of the world is the Sunne, therefore ſleepe is not long to be deſerred after the Sunne ſetting, neither preſently after ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per can ſleepe be wholeſome, for as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith in <hi>lib. Aphoriſmorum, à cibis ad ſom num conuerſis, caput impletur.</hi> Moreouer, immoderate ſleepe maketh the bodie apt to Palſies, Apoplexies, Falling-ſickneſſe, Rhumes and Apoſtumes: alſo it maketh a dull wit, and a ſlow bodie, and vnapt to honeſt exerciſe: as alſo immoderate watch drieth too much the bodie, and doth wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Animal powers, hindreth digeſtion, and maketh the body apt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumptions. Wherefore, in theſe two things, as well as all other, a diligent care is to be vſed, the moderation is beſt coniected (for it is hard perfectly to know it) by the ſenſible light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all the bodie, eſpecially of the braine, the browes, and the eyes, the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage downe of the meat from the ſtomake, the will to make Vrine, and to goe to the ſtoole: contrariwiſe heauines in the bodie, and alſo in the eyes, &amp; ſauour of the mean
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13777:39"/>
before eaten, doth ſignifie that the ſleepe was not ſufficient. They that are in health, muſt firſt ſleepe on the right ſide, becauſe the meate may come to the liuer, which is to the ſtomack as a fire vnder the pot, and thereby is digeſted. To them which haue but weake digeſtion, it is good to ſleepe proſtrate on their bellies, or to haue their pare hands on their ſtomackes, and to lye vpright on the backe, is to bee vtterly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Accidents and Affections of the minde.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THoſe things being alreadie declared, by the which the health of the body is to be preſerued: I will now proceed to the Phyſike of the minde: for as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of the minde doe follow the paſſions of the bodie, as wee may ſee and behold in drunkards, as <hi>Horace</hi> ſaith,
<q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>—nam corpus onuſtum</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Heſternis vitijs animum quoque praegrauat ipſum</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Atque affligit humi aiuinae particulam aurae.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>So on the other ſide, the body is affected
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13777:40"/>
from the paſſions of the minde, and is ſaid therewith to conſent, as is manifeſt in the affects of loue and ſorow. And ſeeing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the paſſions of the minde, and bodie, are ſo conioined and linked together with a naturall band, we muſt as <hi>Auicen</hi> ſaith, haue a diligent care to our minde, if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to auoid diſeaſes, which alſo <hi>Galen</hi> held before him, ſaying, that wee muſt abſtaine from the intemperance and deformity of all the paſſions and affections of the mind: anger and ſorrow, furiouſneſſe and feare, enuy and thought, do alienate and bring a man from the vſe of reaſon, and do greatly transforme him from the ſtate and order, that is according to nature, for moderate mirth helpeth very much to accompliſh all the offices and functions of the minde, to further and make excellent the concoction. As on the contrary, ſorrow and heauineſſe is the greateſt hinderance and let to it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware therefore of heauineſſe and deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Spiritus triſtis exiccat oſſa: cor laetum exhilerat mentem.</hi> Therefore giue your ſelues to honeſt mirth and Chriſtianlike ioy: for as <hi>Auicen</hi> ſaith, the often vſe of mirth diſpoſeth a man to be merry, and thereof commeth no ſmall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13777:40"/>
profit, but commodities very many. Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row alſo is ſo great an Enemie to nature and bodily health, that to reſiſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and the violence thereof, remedies as well out of the holy Scripture, as exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples out of moral Philoſophie are needful. Alſo there be certayne herbs, fruits, and ſpices, that haue the propertie to reſiſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and to comfort the liuely ſpirits. Such are ſimples that do comfort the heart and ſpirits: as for example, the beholding of fayre ſhewes and things that are beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, the hearing of melodious muſicke, ſmelling of ſweet ſauours and fragrant o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, ſuch as in the Summer, the ſmell of Roſe-water; and in Winter with the ſmell of <hi>Lignum Aloes,</hi> which doth comfort the heart and the brayne, and all the other ſenſes very much. But beware of too hot and ſharpe ſauours, for they ſend vapours to the brayne. The taſting, as that which is confected of Sugar, and the iuyce of Pomegranates, of Quinces, or ſome other of like temperature, being not harmefull, neither exceeding in the exceſſe of any qualitie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13777:41"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Ioy.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IOy or gladneſſe of heart doth prolong the life, it maketh the body fat, that is growne leane with care and trouble: And looke what effect hapneth by ſorrow, the ſame hapneth by ſuddaine ioy. And <hi>Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Maximus</hi> reporteth, that a Woman of Rome dyed with ſuddayne ioy. This being conſidered, we muſt auoyd ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie gladneſſe and ſuddayne ioy. And we muſt remember that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world can reioyce vs ſo much, but that ſome occaſion or other may cauſe the ſame to be diſpleaſant vnto vs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of Venus or the act of generation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NOw that I haue ſpoken of Labour, Meate, Drinke, and Sleepe, it now reſteth that I ſpeake ſomewhat of the act of Generation, which delectation muſt be well meaſured by a meane: for if it doe exceed and be vſed intemperately, it doth reſolue the ſpirits and naturall heate about
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13777:41"/>
meaſure, and dryeth vp the radicall moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and ſo dangerous diſeaſes happen to man ſooner, then otherwiſe by nature they would: Therefore, ſeeing in the act of Generation there is ſo great reſolution of Spirits, the exceſſe thereof is carefully to be auoyded, neuertheleſſe great regard muſt bee had of cuſtome. The commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities that come by moderate evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are great, for it procureth appetite to meate, and helpeth digeſtion, it maketh the body more light and nimble, it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth flegme, it quickneth the minde, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth the wit, reneweth the ſenſes, and driueth away ſadneſſe, madneſſe, anger, melancholy: finally, it doth deliuer vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together from leacherous imaginations, and nightly pollutions, which although ſome men ſuppoſe that there is no offence thereby, becauſe of the abundance of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet let vs conſider what is ſaid in <hi>Deuter. cap.</hi> 23. <hi>If there be amongſt you any that is vncleane, by that which commeth from him by night, he ſhall goe out of the Hoaſt, and ſhall not enter into the Hoaſt:</hi> but for this matter let euery man vſe all honeſt and lawfull meanes, to ſuppreſſe the violent force and fury of his burning luſt. Alſo if
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13777:42"/>
a man will abſtayne from meates that be hot and windie, and the drinking of ſweet headie wines, and auoyd the imaginations of <hi>Venus</hi> and ſuch like, he ſhall not eaſily be much aſſailed and tempted with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of any carnall appetite; likewiſe if he earneſtly apply himſelfe to the ſtudy of the holy Scriptures, and morall Phyloſophie, baniſhing idleneſſe, and flie the company of beautiful and amorous Women, he ſhal eaſily auoyd the deſire of luſtfull concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence.</p>
                     <p>Moreouer, there be alſo other meanes to ouer-come carnall luſt, mentioned in <hi>Galen,</hi> as to anoynt the reynes with ſome cooling oyntment made of waxe, oyle of Roſes, and the iuyce of ſome cooling herb, as Houſe-leeke, Lettuce, Purſlane, Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhade or plates of Lead, applyed vpon the reynes, or elſe <hi>Agnus caſtus,</hi> or to eate dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſeede thereof, or the ſeede of Rue, or the herbs themſelues. Alſo <hi>Arnoldus</hi> giueth counſell, If thou wilt quench the heat of luſt, anoynt the genitories with the iuyce of Rue or Perſly, or drinke the iuyce of thoſe herbs. Alſo to ſmell often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to Camphire, is good for the ſame purpoſe, &amp; to ſit vpon the very cold eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13777:42"/>
or a cold ſtone, alſo to plunge the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in cold water or in ſtrong vineger, &amp; therewith to waſh the reynes of the backe and about the lower part of the belly.</p>
                     <p>And to end this diſcourſe of Venery, flie idleneſſe, the greateſt occaſion of lechery, for as the Poet ſaith, with which I wil end:
<q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Otia ſi tollas, periere cupidinis arcus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Contemptae<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> iacent &amp; ſine luce faces.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Certayne precepts for dyet to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued euery day.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="section">
                        <p>HItherto wee haue ſpoken of thoſe things and their lawfull vſe, which things, if they be not rightly vſed, they do alter and change the body, and ouerthrow the naturall ſtate thereof; I will now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer certayne precepts of the order of dyet to be kept for euery day, weekes, moneths, and yeeres, and firſt I will begin with the dyet for euery day.</p>
                        <p>In the beginning when you ariſe from the bed, extend forth all your members, for by this meanes the <hi>animal</hi> ſpirits are drawne to the outward members, the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13777:43"/>
braine is made ſubtill, &amp; the body ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened. Then rubbe the whole body ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what with the palmes, the breſt, back and belly gently, but the armes &amp; legs with the hands, either with warme linnen: next, the head is to be ſcrubbed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fore part to the hinder part very lightly. After you are riſen, I will that you defend with all care and diligence your head, necke, and feete from all cold in the morning; for there is no doubt, but in the morning and euening the cold doth offend more, then it doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noone tide, by reaſon of the weaknes of the Sunne-beames. Put on your clothes neate and cleane: in the Summer ſeaſon, firſt waſh with cleane pure water, before deſcribed; but in the Winter ſeaſon ſit ſomewhat by the fire, not made with turfe or ſtinking coale, but with oake or other wood that burneth cleare, for our bodies are ſomewhat affected with our clothes, and as ſtrength is encreaſed by the vſe of meat and drinke, and our life defended and preſerued; euen ſo our garments doe conſerue the heate of our bodies, and doe driue away colds: ſo that as diet and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel may ſeeme alike, ſo in eyther of them a like diligence is to be preferred.</p>
                        <p>In the Summer-time I chiefly comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13777:43"/>
garments of Harts-skinnes, and Calues-skinnes, for the Hart is a creature of long life, and reſiſteth poyſon and Serpents; therfore I my ſelfe vſe garments of the like ſort for the winter ſeaſon, alſo, neuertheles lined with good linnen. Next, I doe, iudge it not to bee much amiſſe to vſe garments of Silke or Bombace, or of purple; alſo of Martyn or Wolfe-skinnes, or made of Fox skinnes, I ſuppoſe to be good for the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; notwithſtanding in the time of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, apparell of Silke and skinnes is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, becauſe it doth eaſily admit and receiue the contagious ayre, and doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it long. After the body is wel clothed, kembe your head wel with an Iuory comb from the forehead to the back-part, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the comb ſome forty times at the leaſt, then waſh al the inſtruments of the ſences, as the eies, the ears, the noſtrils, the month, the tongue, the teeth, and all the face with cold water; and the eyes are not only to be waſhed, but being open plainly, immerg'd: and the gumme and foulnes of the eie-lids that do there ſtick, to remoue; ſomtimes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to beſprinkle the water with roſe-water or Fenel-water, alſo rub the neek wel with a linnen napkin ſomwhat coorſe, for theſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13777:44"/>
things doe confirme the whole body, it maketh the minde more cheerefull, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the ſight. In this place it pleaſeth me to adioyne ſome dentifrices or clenſers of teeth, waters not only to make the teeth white, but alſo to conſerue them with ſome medicines, alſo to conſerue the ſight.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prescription">
                        <head>A pouder to preſerue the whiteneſſe of the teeth.</head>
                        <p>TAke three egge-ſhels, three drams of red corall, two drams of white ſilke burnt to pouder in a new earthen pot, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon two drams, Cloues one dramme, Pellitorie of Spayne two drammes. Theſe being beaten to fine pouder, rubbe the teeth euery day euening and morning.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prescription">
                        <head>The deſcription of a Dentifrice, which Meſſelina Auguſta vſed: ex ſcribonio largo.</head>
                        <p>TAke Harts horne burnt in a new ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pot, and reduced into pouder one ounce and a halfe, Maſtick one ounce and a halfe, Sal Armoniack ſixe drammes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prescription">
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13777:44"/>
                        <head>To whiten the teeth, and to preſerue them from heate, which was vſed by a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of great name.</head>
                        <p>TAke Aloes one ounce &amp; a halfe, perles one ounce, red Coral and white, Lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Aloes, red Sanders, of euery of them one ounce, Dragons bloud, fine Purſlane one ounce and a halfe, Roch Alum waſhed ſo long in faire water, that it be as cleere as cryſtal, one ounce, maſtick, amber, Myrrhe, of eyther halfe an ounce, the ſhels of water Crabs two drams: let euery one bee bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by it ſelfe into fine powder: then take pure hony of Roſes ſeuenteene ounces, and with the powder aforeſaid let it boyle ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the fire, except the Maſtick, and the Myrrhe, which afterwards mixe therwith, and when it ſhall come to a conſerue in thickneſſe, let it be alwayes ſtirred with a ſticke in the boyling: and when it ſhall be remoued from the fire, let it reſt till it wax cold; then adde the Myrrhe and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, then afterwards keepe it to your vſe in a veſſell of glaſſe: with this Dentifrice if the teeth be rubbed in the morning with a piece of courſe linnen, it doth comfort them, and make them very white.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prescription">
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13777:45"/>
                        <head>Another Dentifrice.</head>
                        <p>TAke red and white Corall, of each one ounce, Pellitory, Mace, Maſtick, of each one ounce, Pomis ſtone and Bole-ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monick, of eyther one ounce; make theſe things into fine powder.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prescription">
                        <head>A Medicine that doth comfort the ſight.</head>
                        <p>TAke perles, which beat into fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then ſtraine them thorow a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth with roſe-water, then inſtill into the eyes certaine drops of the ſame water: ſom in ſtead of the perls, do vſe of the fineſt Sugar with Roſe-water, but I iudge the vſe of Perles to be the better. Theſe things following doe very much profite the eyes, if yee keep them from duſt, ſmoake, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of the aire, the Sun, the cold, from ſtrong winds, from beholding the Sun, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to auoide the multitude of Venery, and repletion of meat and drinke, nor preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after dinner or ſupper to ſleepe; and as it is before ſaid, to bathe and waſh the eyes with cold cleare water, although this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine following be very much approued.</p>
                        <p>Take waters of Veruayne, Betony and Fenell, of euery one, one ounce and a halfe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13777:45"/>
white wine one ounce, Tutla prepared one dram, Sugar-candie two drams, Aloes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patic one dram, womans milke two drams, Camphire halfe a ſcruple: powder that that is to be powdered, and let it remaine in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion for foure and twentie houres, then let them be ſtrained, and therewith waſh the eyes, being ſhut.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <p>Alſo to proſecute our former purpoſe, when you ariſe in the morning, to auoide all ſuperfluities, as well by vrine as by the belly, which doe at the leaſt once euery day. Auoid alſo from the noſtrills and the lungs all filthy matter, as wel by cleanſing, as by ſpittle, and cleanſe the face, head and whole bodie; &amp; loue you to be cleane and well apparelled, for from our cradles let vs abhor vncleannes, which neither nature or reaſon can endure. When you haue done theſe things, remember to powre foorth your praiers vnto God with a cleare voice, that the day may be happie &amp; proſperous vnto you, that God may direct your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the glory of his name, the profit of your Country, &amp; the conſeruation of your bodies. The walk yee gently, &amp; what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſoeuer do ſlip down to the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our parts, being excited by naturall heate,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13777:46"/>
the excretion thereof ſhall the better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
                        <p>As for your buſineſſes, whether they be publike or priuate, let them be done with a certain honeſty, then afterwards let your hunting iourneyes bee performed: apply your ſelues to ſtudie and ſerious buſineſſe the houres of the fore-noone, and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the afternoone, till two or three houres before ſupper, alwaies in your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vſe eyther Corall or yellow Amber, or a Chalcedonium, or a ſweet Pommander, or ſome like precious ſtone to be worne in a ring vpon the little finger of the left hand; haue in your rings eyther a Smaragd, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, or a Draconites, which you ſhall beare for an ornament; for in ſtones, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in hearbes, there is great efficacie and vertue, but they are not altogether percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by vs: hold ſometime in your mouth eyther a Hyacinth, or a Cryſtall, or a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, or pure Gold, or Siluer, or elſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times pure Suger-candy. For <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> doth affirme, and ſo doth <hi>Albertus Magnus,</hi> that a Smaragd worne about the necke, is good againſt the Falling-ſicknes: for ſurely the vertue of an hearbe is great, but much more the vertue of a precious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13777:46"/>
ſtone, which is very likely that they are endued with occult and hidden vertues.</p>
                        <p>Feede onely twice a day, when yee are at mans age; neuertheleſſe to thoſe that are ſubiect to choler, it is lawfull to feede often: beginne alwayes your dinner and ſupper with the more liquid meates, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with drinkes. In the time betweene dinner and ſupper, abſtain altogether from cups, vnleſſe neceſſitie or cuſtome doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the ſame; notwithſtanding the ſame cuſtome being ſo vicious, muſt be by little and little changed.</p>
                        <p>I would not that you ſhould obſerue a certaine houre, eyther for dinners or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, as I haue ſufficiently told you before, leſt that daily cuſtome ſhould be altered into nature: and after this intermiſſion of this cuſtome of nature, hurt may follow; for cuſtome doth imitate nature, and that which is accuſtomable, the very ſame thing is now become naturall.</p>
                        <p>Take your meate in the hotte time of Summer in cold places, but in the Winter let there bee a bright fire, and take it in hotte places, your parlours or chambers being firſt purged and ayred with ſuffumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, which I would not haue you to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13777:47"/>
enter before the ſuffumigation be plainely extinct, leſt you draw the fume by reaſon of the odour.</p>
                        <p>And ſeeing one and the ſame order of diet doth not promiſcuouſly agree with al men: take your meat in order, as is before ſaid, and ſometimes alſo intermit the vſe of meats for a whole day together, becauſe through hunger, the faults of the ſtomack which haue beene taken eyther by much drinking or ſurfetting, or by any other meanes, may be depelled and remoued.</p>
                        <p>By this meanes alſo your bodies ſhal be better accuſtomed to endure and ſuffer hunger and faſting, eyther in iourneyes or wars. Let your ſuppers bee more larger then your dinners, vnleſſe nightly diſeaſes or ſome diſtillations doe afflict you.</p>
                        <p>After meat taken, neither labor in body nor mind muſt be vſed, and waſh the face and mouth with cold water, cleanſe the teeth either with Iuory, or of a Harts horn, or ſome picker of pure ſiluer or gold.</p>
                        <p>After your banquets, paſſe an houre or two in pleaſant talkes, or walke yee very gently and ſoberly, neither vſe much wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings long in the night, but the ſpace of two houres goe to your bed; but if honeſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13777:47"/>
buſines doe require you to watch, then ſleepe afterwards ſo much the longer, that your ſleep may well recompence your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer watchings. Before that you goe to your bed, gently ſmooth down your head, armes, and ſhoulders, the backe and all the bodie, with a gentle and ſoft rubbing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you meane to do it in the morning to moue diſtribution, whoſe time is beſt to be done in the morning.</p>
                        <p>In the Winter ſitting by the fire, put off your garments and drie your feete by the ſire, neuertheleſſe auoid the heate and the ſmoake, becauſe it is very hurtfull both to the lungs and the eyes.</p>
                        <p>In the Winter time warme well your garments at the fire, and warme the linings of the ſame, for it helpeth concoction, and remoueth all humiditie and moyſture. But my father did not allow of this cuſtome, warning men of ſtrength, and thoſe that are borne for the Common-wealth, not to accuſtome themſelues to ſuch kind of ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which doe weaken our bodies. Alſo when you put off your garments to goe to bed, then put away all your waighty cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and lay them aſide, whether they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> publike or priuate, for when all your
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13777:48"/>
members be free from all cares, you ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> then ſleepe the quieter, concoction and the other naturall actions ſhall beſt bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
                        <p>But in the morning when you riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, reſume to your ſelues your forme dayes thoughts and cares, for this precep my Father had often in his mouth, there fore I deliuer it vnto you, as the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> worthy of your obſeruation.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>Certayne precepts againſt Heate and Dryneſſe.</head>
                        <p>EUen as cold is hurtfull to trauailers, ſo is heat alſo, for thereby trauailers be offended, for it hapneth by the want of moyſture, and aboundant heate, for when too much heat doth infeſt trauailers, they doe thereby often-times grow into ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the natural moyſture &amp; ſtrength is diſſolued. Therefore my aduice is, firſt when you trauell, not to vſe much vocife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or talke, for thereby is wont to be drawne thirſt and dryneſſe, againſt which detayne in the mouth cryſtall, corall, ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſugar-candy, or a flint-ſtone that ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth in cold water, the Iulep of Roſes an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Violets with cold water, in like mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13777:48"/>
new ſtick of lickoras, taken freſh out of the earth and chawed, or the drinking of water quencheth the thirſt, alſo new ligs doe mitigate thirſtineſſe, and coole the heate. Pine kernels, the leaues of Purſlane held in the mouth, Straw-berries, Peares, Pruines, Cherries, the ſeedes of Quinces, ſeedes of Lettuce and cucumbers, doe very well diminiſh thirſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>What Age is, and what difference in Age.</head>
                        <p>IN Age there are fiue parts or differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: firſt, child-hood from our birth to fifteene yeeres, and is hot and moyſt. The ſecond, adoleſcence from fifteene to fiue and twentie, a meane and perfect tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature: then youth, from fiue and twentie to fiue and thirtie, and is hot and drie: then middle age, or mans ſtate, from fiue and thirty to forty nine, declining to cold and drie: from nine and forty, the end of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he life, all cold and dry: in all this courſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f the life, there is a continuall change of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> body, but eſpecially euery ſeuenth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>re is called <hi>Annus criticus,</hi> the yeere of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ment. In which time we are in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13777:49"/>
danger, touching life and death. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I would aduiſe you, to haue regard to the change of thoſe times, and to vſe all meanes to preſerue the ſhortneſſe of life, as much as may be.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13777:49"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
